<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>12557</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/xinhuanet_en-fdde405f01e48cb6c6cf65cffc7b6284.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1186</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/19/2012 10:05:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Explore news, videos, and much more based on what your friends are reading and watching. Publish your own activity and retain full control.
Photo illustration of the Los Angeles &amp;hellip;
File photo shows soldiers preparing &amp;hellip;
Australia's decision to bring troops &amp;hellip;
A US soldier patrols a village &amp;hellip;
US Defense Secretary Leon Panetta &amp;hellip;
The United States has swiftly condemned photos of soldiers posing with the mangled corpses of insurgents in Afghanistan, seeking to limit the fallout from the latest scandal involving US troops.
The photographs, which date back to 2010 but were published by the Los Angeles Times on Wednesday, add to a string of damaging incidents that have ignited anti-Western feeling and complicated NATO efforts to withdraw most troops in 2014.
The Taliban on Thursday condemned the photographs as "inhuman" and vowed revenge.
The Taliban "strongly condemns the brutal and inhuman act by the American invading force and their uncultured slaves," a statement from the militants said.
In some of the pictures Afghan police are also seen posing with mangled remains of the Taliban bombers with their US allies.
"This is what the invading Americans teach to their Afghan slaves," the statement said, referring to the members of the Afghan security forces trained and funded by the US-led troops.
US Defense Secretary Leon Panetta said those responsible would be punished but voiced "regret" that the LA Times had decided to publish the images against the Pentagon's wishes, warning that they could prompt a violent backlash.
"I know that war is ugly and it's violent and I know that young people sometimes caught up in the moment make some very foolish decisions," Panetta told a NATO press conference in Brussels.
"I'm not excusing that behavior, but neither do I want these images to bring further injury to our people and to our relationship with the Afghan people."
The LA Times published two of 18 photographs it was given by a soldier who believed they pointed to a breakdown in leadership and discipline that compromised the safety of the troops.
One showed a soldier with a dead insurgent's hand draped on his right shoulder. The other showed soldiers grinning and giving a thumbs-up behind the disembodied legs of a Taliban fighter.
The Times said another set of photos, which it has not yet published, show soldiers from the same division holding a dead man's severed hand with the middle finger raised.
The first incident took place in February 2010, when paratroopers from the 82nd Airborne Division's 4th Brigade Combat Team were sent to an Afghan police station in Zabul province to inspect the remains of an alleged suicide bomber.
The soldiers had orders to try to get fingerprints and possibly scan the irises of the corpse, but instead they posed for pictures next to the Afghan police, holding up or squatting beside the remains, the LA Times reported.
A few months later, the same platoon went to inspect the remains of three insurgents whom Afghan police said had blown themselves up by accident.
The soldiers allegedly involved in the incident served in a unit plagued by leadership problems, according to media reports.
The commander of the brigade was cited for allowing a poor command climate, and a battalion leader and senior enlisted officer were relieved of their posts after showing racist and sexist slides in PowerPoint briefings, the Army Times reported.
The wife of the brigade commander also was reportedly banned from participating in family morale events at the unit's base in Fort Bragg, North Carolina after an investigation found she was harassing other spouses.
Senior US officials insisted the incident did not signal any wider discipline problem, and NATO chief Anders Fogh Rasmussen said the photos did not represent the values of the alliance's mission.
"These events took place apparently a couple of years ago and I consider them an isolated event," he said.
White House spokesman Jay Carney said the photos were "reprehensible" but also said President Barack Obama's administration was "very disappointed" that the paper had published them.
The newspaper's editor, Davan Maharaj, said he had decided to publish a "small but representative selection" of the images because of their news value and to "fulfill our obligation to readers to report vigorously and impartially on all aspects of the American mission in Afghanistan."
Some analysts said the effect of the images would be felt mainly in NATO countries, as most Afghans did not have access to the Internet or television and would not see the pictures.
The episode seemed likely to strain already frayed US-Afghan relations, after a series of incidents in which US troops have been accused of misconduct.
The release in January of video clips online showing American marines urinating on the bodies of Afghan combatants sparked outrage in Kabul.
That was followed by the inadvertent burning of Korans by US soldiers in mid-February, which triggered anti-US protests that claimed 30 lives and may have motivated a surge of "insider" attacks on NATO troops by Afghan forces.
In March, a US soldier allegedly went on a shooting rampage in two Afghan villages, killing 17 people -- mostly women and children -- in what is believed to be the deadliest war crime by a NATO soldier in the decade-long conflict.
NATO has a 130,000-strong military force fighting the Taliban, which has led an insurgency against the Western-backed Kabul government since being toppled from power by a 2001 US-led invasion.
Afghan forces are gradually taking over control of security in the country, with the goal of being in the lead nationwide next year and enabling most foreign troops to depart by the end of 2014.
Afghan 'insider attacks kill 13'
U.S. soldiers from Charlie troop, 4-73 &amp;hellip;
US vows to punish Afghan photo culp &amp;hellip;
An Afghan man claiming he was shot by &amp;hellip;
Police: Nurse lied to fiancé about baby
Is London ready for the Olympics?
Secret Service ousts members from agency
TV legend Dick Clark dies at 82
UNITED NATIONS/BEIRUT (Reuters) - Syria has not fully withdrawn troops and heavy weapons from towns, so far failing to send a "clear signal" about its commitment to peace, the U.N. chief said, underlining &amp;hellip; More »Syria yet to send "clear signal" on peace: U.N. chief
UNITED NATIONS/BEIRUT (Reuters) - Syria has not fully withdrawn troops and heavy weapons from towns, so far failing to send a "clear signal" about its commitment to peace, the U.N. chief said, underlining Western fears over the prospects for a week-old truce. In the first progress report since the Security Council passed &amp;hellip;
BHUBANESWAR, India (Reuters) - India test-fired a long range missile capable of reaching deep into China and Europe on Thursday, thrusting the emerging Asian power into an elite club of nations with intercontinental &amp;hellip; More »India tests long-range missile; capable of reaching China
BHUBANESWAR, India (Reuters) - India test-fired a long range missile capable of reaching deep into China and Europe on Thursday, thrusting the emerging Asian power into an elite club of nations with intercontinental nuclear weapons capabilities. A scientist at the launch site said the launch was successful, minutes after &amp;hellip;
BAGHDAD (Reuters) - At least 24 people were killed and dozens wounded when more than 10 car and roadside bombs, mostly targeting security forces, exploded around Iraq on Thursday, police and hospital sources &amp;hellip; More »At least 24 killed in series of blasts in Iraq
BAGHDAD (Reuters) - At least 24 people were killed and dozens wounded when more than 10 car and roadside bombs, mostly targeting security forces, exploded around Iraq on Thursday, police and hospital sources said. The biggest attack took place in the northern oil city of Kirkuk, where two car bombs aimed at city centre &amp;hellip;
TOKYO (Reuters) - Japan is likely announce at the weekend that it is ready to resume making development loans to Myanmar, a source with direct knowledge of the matter said, a move that would support Myanmar's &amp;hellip; More »Japan near to announcing Myanmar loans restart: source
TOKYO (Reuters) - Japan is likely announce at the weekend that it is ready to resume making development loans to Myanmar, a source with direct knowledge of the matter said, a move that would support Myanmar's nascent democracy and help pay for much-needed infrastructure upgrades. The two countries are in the final stages &amp;hellip;
WASHINGTON (Reuters) - Secretary of State Hillary Clinton offered some hope on Wednesday that North Korea's young leader, Kim Jong-un, may yet change course despite the reclusive Communist state's recent &amp;hellip; More »Too early to tell on North Korean leader: Clinton
WASHINGTON (Reuters) - Secretary of State Hillary Clinton offered some hope on Wednesday that North Korea's young leader, Kim Jong-un, may yet change course despite the reclusive Communist state's recent rocket launch and the threat of a new nuclear test. In an interview with CNN's "The Situation Room," Clinton said it &amp;hellip;
Get breaking news, videos, blogs and more at ABC News. More »Breaking News from ABC News
Credit card companies offer huge bonuses. More »If you have stellar credit
How the Supreme Court’s decision on health care could limit government for a generation. More »A bigger case
These flexible online degrees could help you go to school on your terms.
Thinking about going back to school? Find out which online degrees rank highest in popularity.
</text>
</article>