<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>1852</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/news-yahoo-fe8138b9f1da91b515ba71c6d3a6c137.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1029</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>12/6/2011 2:52:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>By Amir Shah and Rahim Faiez
Updated: 8:41 a.m. on Tuesday, December 6, 2011
KABUL, Afghanistan (AP) &amp;mdash; A suicide bomber struck a crowd  of Shiite worshippers at a mosque in Kabul on Tuesday, killing at least  55 people in the deadliest of two attacks on a Shiite holy day &amp;mdash; the  first major sectarian assaults since the fall of the Taliban a decade  ago.
Four other Shiites were killed in the northern city of  Mazar-i-Sharif when a bomb strapped to a bicycle exploded as a convoy of  Afghan Shiites was driving down the road, shouting slogans for the  festival known as Ashoura. Health Ministry spokesman Sakhi Kargar gave  the death toll and said 21 people also were wounded in that attack.
The shrine, which is near the presidential palace,  was packed with worshippers, and dozens more were crammed into the  courtyard. One witness said the bomber was at the end of a line and  detonated his explosives near one of the gates to the shrine.
The  Ministry of Interior said 55 were killed &amp;mdash; including two women and four  children. Sayed Kabir Amiri, who is in charge of Kabul hospitals, said  more than 160 were wounded in the blast. He said casualties were taken to  several hospitals and the toll could rise.
The  Taliban strongly condemned the two attacks and said in a statement to  news organizations that it deeply regretted that innocent Afghans were  killed and wounded.
Afghan President Hamid Karzai, speaking at a  news conference after meeting German Chancellor Angela Merkel in Berlin,  said the attack was unprecedented in scope.
Mohammad Bakir  Shaikzada, the top Shiite cleric in Kabul, said he could not remember a  similar attack having taken place on such a scale.
The last incident of violence between Shiites and  Sunnis following the U.S. invasion 10 years ago occurred in early 2006,  during Ashoura commemorations in the western city of Herat. During those  riots, blamed on Islamic extremists, five people were killed and more  than 50 injured.
Story Continues &amp;rarr;
Copyright 2011 The Associated Press. All rights reserved. This material may not be published, broadcast, rewritten or redistributed.
By Bill Gertz - The Washington Times
By Patrice Hill - The Washington Times
By Dave Boyer and Stephen Dinan - The Washington Times
By Gary Dettloff  and Michael Hamrick
Permanently cutting corporate taxes would stuff America's stocking with offshore cash
By Amir Shah and Rahim Faiez - Associated Press
updated 37 minutes ago
A suicide bomber struck a crowd of Shiite worshippers at a mosque in Kabul on ...
By Andrea Billups - The Washington Times
By Jim McElhatton - The Washington Times
The U.S. Postal Service moved to change first-class mail delivery standards for the first time ...
Independent voices from the TWT Communities
The “Silver Tsunami” created by aging Baby Boomers is hitting America.  Let’s explore how we adjust to it, enjoy it and defy negative expectations about age.
Covering the world of soccer, including the World Cup, Major League Soccer, D.C. United and the English Premier League and other interesting sporting events.
Join the Communities and submit your column in response to one written, or on something totally new and unique.  We want to hear from you
Are there profound differences between the Left and the Right?  You betcha.
Occupy D.C. protesters, police clash over structure20 Photos
Redskins lose late to the Jets22 Photos
Capitals lose to Penguins, 2-110 Photos
National Christmas Tree lighting14 Photos
Falls Church family wins treehouse appeal11 Photos
Capitol Christmas tree arrives11 Photos
Redskins squeeze out a win15 Photos
google_ad_client = "pub-9012993659965611"
google_ad_slot = "7027609907"
google_ad_width = 728;
google_ad_height = 15;
</text>
</article>