<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>31544</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/news-yahoo-cfc81eb5c2428885b16e5fbb0782a8d4.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g304</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/27/2012 9:28:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Welcome back,   (log out?)
Top Israeli officials have refused to meet the US envoy to the P5+1 group, who arrived in Jerusalem with a report on recent talks with Iran. The diplomatic démarche comes as relations between the two countries strain over Tehran’s nuclear ambitions.
Negotiations between the P5+1 group and Iran failed to produce a result as both sides refused to budge on the nuclear issue. Tehran insists that nuclear enrichment is its “undeniable right,” while Western powers snubbed Iranian demands to remove sanctions
Sources from inside Washington, DC are telling the international media that Israeli leadership is upset with US President Barack Obama’s handling of Iran’s alleged nuclear threat and may take military action before the November election.
Published: 27 May, 2012, 23:24
Leon Panetta (AFP Photo / Saul Loeb / Files)
Leon Panetta has stated that the US is ready to do everything it can to prevent Iran from developing a nuclear weapon. The American envoy to Israel earlier said that the military option is “fully available” and the necessary planning has been done.
­“We will do everything we can to prevent them from developing a weapon,” Panetta told ABC News.
Panetta thus confirmed US Ambassador Dan Shapiro's comments on Israel's Army Radio on May 17, that Washington has a military contingency plan in case “diplomatic talks” fail to “pressure” Iran successfully. Shapiro said the option is not only “fully available", but “ready.”
Now, a week on, Panetta said US officials “have plans to be able to implement any contingency we have to in order to defend ourselves.”
However, Panetta said that the US still hopes that the conflict over Iran’s nuclear ambitions can be “resolved diplomatically.”
Israel is the only country insisting on using military force to pressure Iran away from a suspected atomic weapon.
Tel Aviv reaffirmed its position on May 23, the first day of a new round of talks between the P5+1 group and Iran. Defense Minister Ehud Barak said the negotiations only let Iran to buy time and get in the way of Washington and Tel Aviv.
The next day, even before the negotiations were officially ended, Israeli leadership backtracked on a promise not to attack Iran before America’s November presidential election.
Meanwhile, IAEA suspicions towards Iran remain unresolved.
Straight after the two days of negotiations in Baghdad, the IAEA suspected that Iran had raised its enrichment threshold slightly closer to weapons-grade level. The reason for such accusations was traces of uranium enriched up to 27 per cent reportedly found at the Fordo plant.
However, Iran responded that the find was a technical glitch.
Ali Asghar Soltanieh, Tehran's envoy to the IAEA, said the finding’s been blown out of proportion for political reasons.
Iran’s nuclear chief Fereidoun Abbasi said on Sunday that there was no need to halt production of uranium enriched to 20 per cent, as Iran produces “only as much 20 per cent material” as it needs. The statement came in response to the group of six's demands that Iran suspend 20 per cent enrichment in exchange for a US-supported package that would include radioactive material and spare civilian plane parts. But Tehran said they offered too little in return. Abbasi also touched upon a possible visit to the Parchin military site by IAEA observers, saying it would not come any time soon. “We haven’t been convinced yet. No reasons and documents have been presented to enable us to arrange a visit to Parchin, which is a military site,” he was quoted by ISNA as saying.
The UN Security Council has convened for an urgent session in New York to hear a report over the shelling in Syria's Houla, which killed at least 90 people on Friday. Britain and France are pressing for a statement condemning the Syrian government.
Different estimates say between 30,000 and 100,000 people have flooded the streets of Tbilisi in the largest in three years of anti-government demonstrations in Georgia's capital.
and Iran is preparing to show one of it's fingers to USRAEL... which one? anyone they DESERVE
        &amp;copy; Autonomous Nonprofit Organization "TV-Novosti", 2005-2012. All rights reserved.
</text>
</article>