<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>12916</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/trust-b34ff7903ed333dbcb90b1ddc5c1cd82.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1070</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/19/2012 4:08:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Explore news, videos, and much more based on what your friends are reading and watching. Publish your own activity and retain full control.
BRUSSELS (AP) — The European Union will suspend most sanctions against Myanmar for a year while it assesses the country's progress toward democracy, officials said Thursday.
The officials said that while the decision would be formally taken by the EU's 27 foreign ministers when they meet Monday in Luxembourg, it has already been agreed in principle. The officials spoke on condition of anonymity to divulge information not yet officially announced.
The sanctions will be suspended for a year, with the possibility of a review in six months, the officials said. The sanctions currently target more than 800 companies and nearly 500 people, and also include the suspension of some development aid.
An embargo on arms and equipment that can be used for internal repression will remain in place, however.
Myanmar, long a dictatorship, appears to be undergoing a remarkable transition. Last year, the junta ceded power to a new government that has embarked on widely praised reforms, including opening a dialogue with opposition leader Aung San Suu Kyi and allowing her to run for — and win — a seat in parliament.
British Prime Minister David Cameron visited Myanmar, also known as Burma, earlier this month, becoming the first leader of a major western country to visit the nation since the relaxation of military rule. EU foreign policy chief Catherine Ashton plans to travel to the country at the end of the month.
Myanmar's pro-democracy leader Aung &amp;hellip;
Myanmar begins historic polling likely &amp;hellip;
An official smiles behind gates of an &amp;hellip;
Suu Kyi to meet Myanmar President Thein &amp;hellip;
T-Mobile spokeswoman's edgy makeover
Flying fish almost silenced Isaac Newton
Why 'Matilda' child star quit acting
Cruise line under fire in tragedy at sea
OSLO (Reuters) - Norwegian anti-Islamic fanatic Anders Behring Breivik told a court on Thursday he had planned for even bigger attacks before killing 77 people and had prepared for the massacre by playing &amp;hellip; More »Norwegian killer says planned far larger attacks
OSLO (Reuters) - Norwegian anti-Islamic fanatic Anders Behring Breivik told a court on Thursday he had planned for even bigger attacks before killing 77 people and had prepared for the massacre by playing computer games. On the fourth day of his trial for the attacks in July, Breivik said he had considered bombing the annual &amp;hellip;
BEIRUT (Reuters) - Syria and the United Nations signed an agreement on Thursday on terms for hundreds of observers to monitor a ceasefire, but diplomatic wrangling still lies ahead to persuade the West &amp;hellip; More »Syria-U.N. agree on terms of monitoring mission
BEIRUT (Reuters) - Syria and the United Nations signed an agreement on Thursday on terms for hundreds of observers to monitor a ceasefire, but diplomatic wrangling still lies ahead to persuade the West the mission will have the clout needed to ensure peace. An advance party of half a dozen U.N. observers are already in &amp;hellip;
BAGHDAD (Reuters) - More than 20 bombs hit cities and towns across Iraq on Thursday, killing at least 36 and wounding almost 150, police and hospital sources said, raising fears of sectarian strife in &amp;hellip; More »At least 36 killed in wave of Iraq blasts
BAGHDAD (Reuters) - More than 20 bombs hit cities and towns across Iraq on Thursday, killing at least 36 and wounding almost 150, police and hospital sources said, raising fears of sectarian strife in a country whose authorities are keen to show they can now maintain security. In Baghdad, three car bombs, two roadside bombs &amp;hellip;
LONDON (Reuters) - British police arrested three people, including the royal editor of Rupert Murdoch's Sun tabloid, a source familiar with the situation said, in an escalation of a long-running phone &amp;hellip; More »Sun journalist held ahead of showdown for Murdochs
LONDON (Reuters) - British police arrested three people, including the royal editor of Rupert Murdoch's Sun tabloid, a source familiar with the situation said, in an escalation of a long-running phone hacking scandal which reaches into Britain's political establishment. Thursday's arrests and the fact they stemmed from &amp;hellip;
KHARKIV, Ukraine (Reuters) - Ukraine's former prime minister Yulia Tymoshenko went on trial on Thursday and faces up to 12 more years in prison if convicted of fresh graft charges, in a case that once &amp;hellip; More »Ukraine's Tymoshenko on trial again, West warns of isolation
KHARKIV, Ukraine (Reuters) - Ukraine's former prime minister Yulia Tymoshenko went on trial on Thursday and faces up to 12 more years in prison if convicted of fresh graft charges, in a case that once again drew harsh criticism from an attending Western human rights official. She refused to attend Thursday's hearing citing &amp;hellip;
Get breaking news, videos, blogs and more at ABC News. More »Breaking News from ABC News
View the latest slideshow galleries on Yahoo! News. More »Photos of the day
Credit card companies offer huge bonuses. More »If you have stellar credit
These flexible online degrees could help you go to school on your terms.
Thinking about going back to school? Find out which online degrees rank highest in popularity.
</text>
</article>