<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>11224</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/jpost-f709c08ad161612e435b94110761664a.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g571</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/16/2012 5:38:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Mohammadi said one militant arrested in the east had confessed that the fighters had ties to the Haqqani network, a ruthless Taliban-linked insurgent group based in Pakistan, and blamed for most high-profile assaults in the Afghan capital.
A Taliban spokesman said the Haqqani network had played no role in the attack. Zabihullah Mujahid told Reuters that the insurgents had planned the offensives for months, creating model replicas of targeted buildings so that fighters could rehearse their attacks.
Bystanders outside the high-rise at the edge of the diplomatic district swore the fighters were Pakistani, although there was no evidence. "You can tell he was Pakistani, he is so thin," said a teenager, Najibullah, after peering into the guard cabin of a nearby compound belonging to the intelligence services, where a sixth insurgent's body was stowed.
The insurgent had been shot dead in an apparent diversionary attack that launched the fighting. As the militants drove up to the building site in an SUV, one fighter jumped down into the street and ran to attack the heavily defended gate of the National Directorate of Security complex, said Major Sayed Abdullah, a National Directorate of Security (NDS) commando who was at the gate.
He said the fighter was killed almost immediately, but the attack gave his comrades time to take up their positions. After a grenade bounced without exploding, they rammed the site gate open with their car.
Guards dropped their weapons and ran to join unarmed construction workers when they saw the militants pull up. They spent several hours cowering in the basement, and were taken into police custody, Abdullah said.
There are strong suspicions that the fighters must have stashed weapons and other supplies in the building in preparation for the attack, because their ammunition held out so long, another intelligence official said. Bullet casings were scattered throughout the building, and empty water bottles and cartons of cream lay near a grenade and a tangle of wires that soldiers warned could be a booby trap.
Hours after the attack ended, US troops with sniffer dogs checked the building for undetonated explosives, as security officials inured to violence snapped pictures of the bodies and discussed the support the fighters must have received.
"Look at their expensive snacks," said a police general, Khalil Momenzada, pointing at a half-eaten bag of cashews that lay next to shattered teacups and an upended thermos. "Of course someone must have helped them, prepared all these things for them."
</text>
</article>