<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>26194</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/jrep-4e2586973c0e76af32b4f04828c417da.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g462</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/22/2012 12:11:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Celebrations for National Day take place a day after attack on parade rehearsal left 96 soldiers dead in Sana'a
Yemeni leaders have led a sombre ceremony to mark the country's national day, scaling back the celebrations a day after a suicide bombing killed nearly 100 soldiers during a rehearsal for a military parade.
The president, Abed Rabbo Mansour Hadi, along with top military commanders, government officials and foreign diplomats, took part in a small, symbolic parade held inside Sana'a's Aviation Academy. Hadi sat behind a bulletproof glass shield with his armoured car parked nearby.
Security concerns were paramount at the ceremony following Monday's suicide attack, when a Yemeni soldier detonated a bomb hidden in his uniform during a rehearsal for a military parade for National Day, which marks the 1990 reunification of north and south Yemen. Ninety-six soldiers were killed and at least 200 wounded in one of the deadliest attacks in the capital in years.
Al-Qaida's branch in Yemen claimed responsibility for the bombing, saying in an emailed statement that the suicide attack was intended to avenge a US-backed offensive against al-Qaida in a swath of southern Yemen seized by the militant movement last year.
Addressing the crowd on Tuesday, the chief of staff of the Yemeni military, Major General Ahmed Ali al-Ashwal, vowed the nation would not be deterred by such attacks.
"We will not let terrorism destroy our future and dreams," he said.
Ashwal was the only official to speak at the ceremony, which was drastically scaled back because of security concerns. The parade was cut from three hours to one hour, a fly-over by fighter jets was cancelled and only cadets from the police and aviation academies participated in the programme.
Yemenis were marking National Day for the first time without their longtime ruler Ali Abdullah Saleh, who held power for nearly 30 years. Saleh was forced to step down after a year-long uprising in which hundreds of thousands of Yemenis took to the streets demanding his removal.
</text>
</article>