<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>373</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/nowlebanon-f5f297f60807ba3b5bd94447d9cf01b2.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g608</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>11/18/2011 4:15:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Syria has agreed "in principle" to allow an Arab League observer mission into the country but has asked for certain amendments, the pan-Arab bloc has said.
The announcement came as fresh protests took place across the country calling on nations to expel Syrian ambassadors from their countries.
Walid al-Muallem, Syria's foreign minister, sent a letter to Arab League chief Nabil al-Arabi requesting changes to the league's proposal which entailed sending 500 observers to Damascus to try to help end the bloodshed, the league said.
"These amendments are currently being studied," Arabi said in a statement on Friday, but he did not specify what they were.
Activists reported that at least 15 people were killed on Friday by security forces, including two children. Most of the dead were in the southern province of Daraa.
On Wednesday, Arab leaders gave Syrian President Bashar al-Assad three days to halt his "bloody repression" of protests or risk sanctions.
The 22-member bloc voted at an extraordinary meeting in Cairo on Saturday to suspend Syria until Assad implemented the deal to end the crackdown, which has left at least 3,500 people dead since March, according to UN figures.
Activists said that Syrian troops have shelled two northern villages overnight after an attack by army defectors on forces loyal to Assad, in the first report of such an incident during the eight-month uprising.
Eight villagers were injured when tank shells and heavy mortars fell for three hours on Tal Minnij and Maarshamsheh and surrounding farmland, activists told the Reuters news agency.
"Hundreds of families have left. Electricity and internet services have been cut off," said one activist who gave his first name as Raed.
Army defectors had earlier attacked a building housing security forces near army depots in the Wadi al-Deif area on the edge of the town of Maarat al-Numaan, 290km north of Damascus, the activists said.
The town, on the Damascus-Aleppo highway, has seen regular street protests demanding Assad's removal and raids by security forces to put down the demonstrations.
In the last few weeks, residents say a growing number of army defectors have been defending Maarat al-Numaan and attacking army patrols and roadblocks.
The authorities blame the violence on foreign-backed armed groups who they say have killed more than 1,100 soldiers and police.
Syria's official news agency said troops carried out a "qualitative operation" in the region, arresting 58 wanted people and seizing rifles and bomb detonators. The agency said eight "of the most wanted terrorist" were arrested on Thursday in the central city of Homs, where tanks have been deployed.
'Real civil war'While Arab and Western countries sought to increase pressure on Assad, Russia, which has a naval base, major oil concessions and military personnel in Syria, stood by the Syrian leader.
Sergei Lavrov, the Russian foreign minister, whose country is one of Syria's few remaining foreign allies, said demands for Assad's removal would destroy the initiative, which calls for dialogue between the Syrian government and its foes.
Lavrov said a raid on Wednesday by the Free Syrian Army on an Airforce Intelligence complex on the outskirts of the capital Damascus was "already completely similar to real civil war".
Opposition sources said Syrian army defectors had killed or wounded 20 security police in the early-morning attack, the first of its kind in the revolt against Assad.
Mark Toner, the US state department spokesman, rejected the suggestion that Syria was virtually in civil war, saying: "We believe it's very much the Assad regime carrying out a campaign of violence, intimidation, and repression against innocent protesters."
Content on this website is for general information purposes only.
</text>
</article>