<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>25024</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/jrep-4e2586973c0e76af32b4f04828c417da.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g462</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/21/2012 1:12:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>New feature Personalise your news, save articles to read later and customise settings View Demo
If you have trouble accessing our login form below, you can go to our login page.
The Sydney Morning Herald
A Yemeni soldier dressed in uniform has blown himself up in the middle of an army battalion in Sanaa, killing at least 50 troops and wounding dozens of others.
Monday's suicide attack was the deadliest in the country's capital since newly-elected President Abdrabuh Mansur Hadi pledged in February to oust al-Qaeda militants from Yemen's mostly lawless and restive southern and eastern provinces.
"There are at least 50 dead and the toll could rise," an official said, speaking on condition of anonymity, adding that all the casualties were soldiers.
So far, no one has claimed responsibility for the blast, which witnesses say was heard across the city and caused panic.
The unidentified bomber detonated his explosives in Sabeen Square as soldiers from the government's central security forces, commanded by a nephew of former president Ali Abdullah Saleh, rehearsed for an army parade to mark the 22nd anniversary of the unification of north and south Yemen, according to the official.
Yemen's defence minister, Mohammed Nasser Ahmed, was present at the time of the explosion but escaped unharmed.
Witnesses said human remains were scattered across the square. An AFP correspondent said dozens of ambulances rushed to evacuate the dead and wounded.
Hadi was expected to give a speech at a military ceremony scheduled for Tuesday. It remains unclear now if the parade will take place.
The bombing comes 10 days into an army offensive against al-Qaeda in Yemen's restive southern Abyan province, where the jihadists have seized control of a string of towns and cities since May last year.
Since the offensive began, 213 people have been killed, according to a tally compiled by AFP, including 147 al-Qaeda fighters, 31 military personnel, 18 local militia and 17 civilians.
The offensive followed days after the White House announced that a plot by al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP) to blow up a US airliner had been foiled.
It said a double agent spent weeks with AQAP before handing over information allowing the United States to launch a drone strike on May 6 that killed Fahd al-Quso, a senior figure wanted for the 2000 bombing of the USS Cole in Yemen.
2 people are reading this now.
</text>
</article>