<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>12938</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/independent-ie-72fd1950feb1027f88f74c4dd5db43dd.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1065</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/19/2012 5:20:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>The Security Council was to meet in New York on Thursday to take up Mr. Ban's recommendations, and it is expected to vote on them as early as next week, diplomats said. The proposed name of the formal mission is the U.N. Supervision Mission in Syria, or UNSMIS.
"Given the lack of presence on the ground other than the first members of the Advance Team who arrived three days ago, it remains a challenge to assess accurately unconfirmed and conflicting reports of developments in Syria," Mr. Ban said.
France, which is hosting a "Friends of Syria" summit in Paris, took a tougher line in negotiations over Syria Thursday, with French President Nicolas Sarkozy calling Syrian President Bashar Assad a "liar," while the French foreign minister urged a more robust international observer mission than Damascus has been willing to accept, according to the AP. A dozen top diplomats from the U.S., Europe and Arab states are looking for ways of helping Mr. Annan's peace plan to end the violence in Syria.
In Syria, activists said regime forces took control of a southern town and shot at activists in another soon after international observers left. Protesters chanted anti-government slogans for the observers to hear, the AP said.
Despite the latest reports of fighting, both sides have continued to "express their commitment to a cessation of armed violence" and have agreed to cooperate with the U.N. observers, he said. The U.N. monitors, if deployed under favorable conditions, could uphold the commitments of the parties to the cease-fire and to the start of long-term political talks, Mr. Ban said.
The advance team of monitors that will soon number 30 has already begun to do its work and report its findings, Mr. Ban said.
The observers visited Dera'a on Tuesday and "enjoyed freedom of movement," Mr. Ban reported. "It observed no armed violence or heavy weapons in the city," he said. Nor did the observers see "major military concentrations."
Mr. Fawzi, spokesman for Mr. Annan, said in a statement that the agreement negotiated Thursday with Syria outlines the observers' functions and the "tasks and responsibilities" of the Syrian government, according to AP.  He added that Mr. Annan also is having "similar discussions" with opposition figures to reach agreement on "the tasks and responsibilities of armed opposition groups," AP said.
The advance team on Wednesday visited Jobar, Zamalka and Arbeen in Rif Damascus. "It reported military presence at checkpoints and around some public squares and buildings in all three locations," he said
"Arbeen became tense when a crowd that was part of an opposition demonstration forced United Nations vehicles to a checkpoint," Mr. Ban wrote. "Subsequently, the crowd was dispersed by firing projectiles. Those responsible for the firing could not be ascertained by the United Nations Military Observers."
There were no injuries but a U.N. vehicle was slightly damaged, he said. On Thursday the observers are headed to Rif Da'raa. However, he said the team's request to visit Homs, scene of some of the worst violence in the 13-month old uprising, was denied by the Syrian authorities, "claiming security concerns," Mr. Ban said.
The secretary-general reported that peaceful demonstrations have taken place in various cities "with a more restrained response than in previous incidents of protest, but there were nevertheless attempts to intimidate protesters, including reports of incidents of rifle fire by government troops."
The circumstances of thousands of political detainees remained "unclear and there continue to be reports of significant abuses," he said. "There has been no significant release of detainees," he said, though that should be one part of the U.N.'s six-part peace plan.
"The release of persons arbitrarily detained is a key commitment of the Government under the six point plan that would provide a significant signal of the serious intent of the Government effectively to implement the plan in its entirety and create the conditions for a political solution through peaceful dialogue," Mr. Ban wrote to the council.
On the humanitarian front, Mr. Ban reported that, "no substantive progress has been achieved over the last weeks of negotiations on access to those in need, or in increasing the capacity" of aid organizations in the country.
While Syrian authorities were given responsibility by the Security Council to provide security for the U.N. monitors, Damascus must ensure freedom of movement and the right to private communications with "individuals throughout Syria without retaliation against any person as a result of interaction with the mission," Mr. Ban said.
"Consultations have taken place to explain these principles to the Government of Syria, including fundamental principles of U.N. peacekeeping regarding selection of personnel," the U.N. chief wrote. Syrian officials say they want monitors only from Russia, China, Brazil, India and South Africa.
Mr. Ban is giving Syria 30 days after the Security Council authorizes the mission to conclude an agreement on these terms.
Write to                 Joe Lauria at newseditor@wsj.com
Copyright 2012 Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved
This copy is for your personal, non-commercial use only. Distribution and use of this material are governed by our Subscriber Agreement and by copyright law. For non-personal use or to order multiple copies, please contact Dow Jones Reprints at 1-800-843-0008 or visit
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Europe's bold program to defuse its financial crisis by injecting cash into the banking system is running out of steam.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Bank of America's first-quarter profit slumped 68%, hurt by a $4.8 billion accounting charge related to changes in the value of the bank's debt.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
GlaxoSmithKline launched an unsolicited $2.6 billion offer for longtime research partner Human Genome Sciences.
India successfully tested its most advanced long-range nuclear-capable missile to date, a launch that New Delhi hopes will serve as a deterrent against China.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Save This &amp;darr; More
Do we need religion to have ethics? Is it possible that a world without religion can be, on the whole, a better place to live?
A definition is always a good start, but ...
Should individual income tax withholding be abolished?
Do you think Instagram is worth $1 billion?
Whom should Mitt Romney pick as his running mate?
The latest news and analysis delivered to your in-box. Check the boxes below to sign up.
The email address null is already associated with another account. Please enter a different email address:
Thank you !You will receive  in your inbox.
The latest news and analysis delivered to your in-box. Check the boxes below to sign up.
The email address null is already associated with another account. Please enter a different email address:
Thank you !You will receive  in your inbox.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Your question to the Journal Community Your comments on articles will show your real name  and not a username.Why?
Why use your real name? The Journal Community encourages thoughtful dialogue and meaningful connections between real people. We require the use of your full name to authenticate your identity. The quality of conversations can deteriorate when real identities are not provided.
Create a Journal Community profile to avoid this message in the future. (As a member you agree to use your real name when participating in the Journal Community)
Your participation access with Journal Community has been disabled due to violation of Journal Community Guidelines.
If you feel you have reached this status change in error, please contact TBD@wsj.com
</text>
</article>