<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>19858</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/AP-694e517fb48d955cf0af49117f5ffb03.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g900</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/16/2012 1:52:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Norwegian Major-General Robert Mood, chief of the United Nations Supervision Mission in Syria, speaks to the media at a hotel in Damascus, May 16, 2012. (Xinhua/Hazim)
Norwegian Major-General Robert Mood, chief of the United Nations Supervision Mission in Syria, speaks to the media at a hotel in Damascus, May 16, 2012. (Xinhua/Hazim)
DAMASCUS, May 16 (Xinhua) -- Head of UN observers in Syria Maj. Gen. Robert Mood said Wednesday that the observers whose convoy were struck by a blast in Khan Sheikhoun near the southern Hama province a day earlier have departed from the area and are on their way back.
A convoy of four vehicles with UN observers in them was struck Tuesday afternoon by a blast caused by an improvised explosive device in Khan Sheikhoun area near Hama.
Three of the vehicles were damaged, but no UN personnel was injured, said Ahmad Fawzi, spokesman of the UN-Arab League joint envoy Kofi Annan, adding that the mission has sent a patrol team to the area to bring back the observers.
Mood said earlier Wednesday that the observers are safe and have stayed in Hama overnight.
He expressed gratitude to the Syrian government for facilitating the return of the observers, and renewed calls for halting violence in the country in order to make his mission a success.
Syria's violence extends its reach, undermines UN observer mission
DAMASCUS, May 15 (Xinhua) -- The incessant violence in Syria extended its reach on Tuesday and targeted the UN observers who were supposed to have a "calming effect" in restive Syrian areas.
Shortly after 2 p.m. local time (GMT 1100) on Tuesday, a UN convoy of four vehicles was struck by a blast caused by an improvised explosive device in Khan Sheikhoun area, located near Syria's central province of Hama, Ahmad Fawzi, spokesman of the UN- Arab League joint envoy Kofi Annan, said in a statement obtained by Xinhua.  Full story
Attack on UN convoy in Syria confirmed
UNITED NATIONS, May 15 (Xinhua) -- The United Nations on Tuesday confirmed that a UN peacekeeping convoy of four vehicles in Syria were hit by a blast on the same day, but no UN personnel were injured in the incident, Martin Nesirky, the UN spokesman, told reporters here.
"The UN Supervision Mission in Syria (UNSMIS) reports that, shortly after 2 p.m. local time on Tuesday, an UNSMIS convoy of four vehicles was struck by an explosion from an improvised explosive device in Khan Cheikhoun, near Hama," Nesirky said at a daily news briefing.  Full story
Special Report: Syrian Situation
</text>
</article>