<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>26220</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/alertnet-f38811d5692891a2cba6ffb6a33bf29e.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g237</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/22/2012 12:15:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>10:44AM BST 22 May 2012
Mr Amano said some details still need to be worked out. But he said that Iranian 
  officials will not stand in the way of signing the deal.
He spoke on return from Tehran, after talks on resuming a long-stalled probe 
  into suspicions that Iran secretly worked on developing nuclear weapons.
"A decision was made by me and Mr Jalili to reach an agreement on the 
  structured approach," he said, referring to Iran's lead negotiator Saeed 
"At this stage I can say it will be signed quite soon but I cannot say how 
  soon it will be," he added, describing the agreement as an "important 
Mr Jalili said that the "existing differences will not be an obstacle to the 
  agreement," Mr Amano said, without elaborating.
Iran raises hope of nuclear talks breakthrough
Ahmadinejad should 'open nightclubs', says Iran MP
US admits it has military plan to attack Iran
US is ready to attack Iran, says ambassador
The investigation has been stalled for more than four years, with Iran saying 
  it has never carried out such experiments. Iran denies that it is interested 
  in nuclear weapons, saying it wants nuclear power only to generate energy.
The day before Iran participates in a summit in Baghdad with international 
  negotiators led by Baroness Ashton, the EU's foreign affairs chief, 
  expectations have risen that Tehran is prepared to offer substantial 
  concessions in return for a reversal of punishing international sanctions.
Meanwhile the US Senate backed measures imposing new sanctions targeting 
  Iran's Revolutionary Guard Corps. The bill would require companies that 
  trade on the US stock exchange to disclose any Iran-related business to the 
  Securities and Exchange Commission and would expand penalties for energy and 
  uranium mining joint ventures with Tehran.
The bill also would deny visas and freeze assets on individuals and companies 
  that supply Iran with technology that could be used to crack down on its 
  citizens, such as tear gas, rubber bullets and surveillance equipment.
The House of Representatives passed its version of sanctions legislation in 
Both the Obama administration and the international community have imposed 
  tough sanctions on Iran over its nuclear development program, which Iran 
  maintains is for peaceful purposes only.
"Any comprehensive policy that seeks to end Iran's effort to acquire a 
  nuclear weapon needs to convince the rulers in Tehran that their survival is 
  in question," Republican Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell said in 
  a statement. "While sanctions are one part of convincing the Supreme 
  Leader that the costs of pursuing this weapon outweigh any perceived 
  benefit, Senate Republicans insisted that the Senate pass nothing less than 
  the president's commitment that all options are on the table, in order to 
  prevent any contrary perception that silence on the use of force would have 
Last Thursday, Senate Republicans blocked consideration of the bill, insisting 
  that it include language stating that the use of military force is an 
  option, as Obama has said. Negotiations through the weekend produced a bill 
  that was acceptable to Democrats and Republicans.
Democratic Sen. Bob Menendez, a leading proponent of tough penalties on Iran, 
  said the legislation sends a clear message to Tehran in advance of the 
  talks: "Provide a real and verifiable plan for the complete dismantling 
  of your nuclear weapons program, or Washington will further tighten the 
Said Republican Sen. Mark Kirk, "Today the US Senate put Iranian leaders 
  on notice that they must halt all uranium enrichment activities or face 
  another round of economic sanctions from the United States."
How Hollywood's hippest actress became a transsexual assassin.
Featured Advertising
Search for a property
MORE FROM TELEGRAPH.CO.UK
&amp;copy; Copyright of Telegraph Media Group Limited 2012
Terms and Conditions
</text>
</article>