<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>5956</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/nation-e7e2b48170f33c10850bf94f483bc988.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g777</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/5/2012 6:25:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>The United Nations-Arab League peace envoy for Syria has briefed the UN General Assembly about a ceasefire meant to come into force on April 12.  Kofi Annan said both sides had expressed their commitment to the plan.
United Nations-Arab League envoy Kofi Annan told the UN General Assembly on Thursday that both Syrian government forces and the rebels had committed to a ceasefire starting April 12.
Syrian forces are meant to halt new troop movements and end the use of heavy weapons by April 10, and the rebels have indicated they will cease attacks within 48 hours of that, by 6:00 a.m. local time on April 12.
Despite signs of continued violence since Syrian President Bashar al-Assad's pledge earlier this week to implement the peace plan, Annan said Damascus had instructed its forces to start pulling back from populated centers.
"All parties must immediately cease all violence," Annan said via a video link from Geneva to the UN General Assembly in New York, adding that the ceasefire is the top priority in his six-point plan that Damascus had agreed to implement.
"I urge the government and the opposition commanders to issue clear instructions so that the message reaches across the country, down to the fighter and soldier at the local level,"  he told the General Assembly.
Annan acknowledged that there were still “alarming levels” of deaths being reported, despite the pledged peace plan.
UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon, meanwhile, said that the violence in Syria had not stopped and that the conflict was worsening.
"Despite the Syrian government's acceptance of the joint special envoy's (Annan's) plan of initial proposals to resolve the crisis, the violence and assaults in civilian areas have not stopped. The situation on the ground continues to deteriorate," Ban said.
Annan has asked a Norwegian major general to negotiate the deployment of UN monitors in Syria for any ceasefire between the two sides.
Major General Robert Mood has reportedly arrived in Syria. A spokesman for Annan's peace envoy said the UN is already asking members to contribute 200 to 250 soldiers to monitor a ceasefire starting on April 10.
A peacekeeping force of this sort would first have to be approved by the 15-nation Security Council.
"A cessation of violence is an important beginning, " Annan said. "I am acutely aware of the grave situation on the ground. ... Let us stop the killing and start serious political dialogue, for the wellbeing of the Syrian people.”
tm/pfd (dpa, Reuters, AFP, AP)
Firefighters put out two fires blaze after smoke alarm triggered the shut down of a French nuclear reactor. Officials said there were no injuries or consequences for the environment.
The United Nations-Arab League peace envoy for Syria has briefed the UN General Assembly about a ceasefire meant to come into forces on April 12.  Kofi Annan said both sides had expressed their commitment to the plan.
The man chosen by Egypt's Muslim Brotherhood to run for president in next month's election has officially registered as a candidate. He has pledged to introduce sharia law to the country if elected.
Top generals from Mali's West African neighbors have convened in the Ivory Coast to discuss a possible intervention. A contingent of 2,000 troops has been put on standby, though it's not clear for what purpose.
</text>
</article>