<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>22706</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/trust-02fe532a3600a71fc753db9d2fd0a8f1.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g425</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/19/2012 10:45:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>By May MasangkayWASHINGTON, May 19, Kyodo
Leaders of the Group of Eight countries agreed Friday that North Korea will find itself more isolated if it continues to take provocative steps, while urging Iran to prove to the global community that its nuclear program is peaceful, a senior U.S. official said.
During their working dinner, U.S. President Barack Obama and leaders from the other G-8 countries -- Britain, Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan and Russia -- also discussed global security concerns such as the escalating violence in Syria.
The discussions took place during a working dinner of the two-day G-8 summit through Saturday at the U.S. presidential retreat in Camp David, Maryland.
The G-8 summit comes amid speculation that North Korea may conduct a third nuclear test following its failed rocket launch on April 13 in defiance of U.N. Security Council resolutions.
Being the only Asian country in the G-8 framework, Japan has been keen to put North Korea on the agenda.
Noda was quoted by Japan's Foreign Ministry as saying that the G-8 nations and other members of the international community should issue a strong message to North Korea that they cannot tolerate Pyongyang's provocative actions.
On another security challenge, the U.S. official noted the ''sense of urgency'' in dealing with the Iranian nuclear issue and said the ''onus is on the Iranians to take concrete steps to demonstrate that their program is peaceful.''
In addressing concerns over Iran's suspected nuclear weapons development program, the International Atomic Energy Agency has been requesting that Iran comply with verification measures regarding its nuclear program.
Iran has insisted its nuclear program is for peaceful purposes, but Western countries view Iran's uranium enrichment program as a cover for the development of nuclear weapons. Because of this, the United States and Europe have imposed sanctions on Tehran, as part of global efforts to apply pressure on it.
Referring to measures to take further sanctions against Iran, Noda said there is a ''need to keep tabs on the impact of (this) pressure on the world economy,'' according to the ministry.
The G-8 leaders' discussions come ahead of an important meeting of five permanent members of the U.N. Security Council plus Germany next Wednesday to discuss the Iranian nuclear issue.
Turning to the escalating violence in Syria, the U.S. official said there was no disagreement among the G-8 leaders on the need for ''some political transition'' in Syria.
The United Nations has estimated that more than 9,000 people have been killed since an uprising against President Bashar al-Assad began last year.
The G-8 leaders also underscored the need to fully implement a six-point plan brokered by U.N.-Arab League envoy Kofi Annan to bring peace to Syria.
On Saturday, the leaders are expected to discuss Europe's sovereign debt crisis, food security in Africa, and Afghanistan's economic development.
</text>
</article>