<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>16657</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/dailystar-LB-adc1ab5a728a058fb0f725bfcf39fe8a.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g964</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/11/2012 9:37:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Saturday 12 May 2012
8:16PM BST 11 May 2012
"Initial details indicate that the Aleppo blast was targeting the local 
  branch of the ruling Baath party and there is no information until now on 
  the number of victims that fell in the explosion," said British-based Syrian 
  Observatory for Human Rights.
Rami Abdel Rahman, of the Observatory said unidentified gunmen shot dead a 
  guard outside the Baath party office as they drove by in a vehicle soon 
  after the explosion.
"The blast was powerful but we do not know what was the origin of the 
  explosion," said Abdel Rahman. "We can confirm one death - the guard of the 
  Baath party office."
He said there was a chance that the explosion was caused by a sound bomb.
Earlier, state TV said the army foiled a would-be suicide attack a day after 
  twin bombings in Damascus left scores dead.
Anti-regime protests break out across Syria
Damascus resident on moment bombs struck
UN condemns deadly bomb attacks in Damascus
Syria: Damascus rocked by double car bombing killing 55
Syria: international action becoming more unlikely
55 killed in Syria's most deadly attacks since uprising
Eleven people were killed across the country, in areas including central Hama 
  and southern Daraa, where an 11-year-old child died from sniper fire, 
  according to the Syrian Observatory for Human Rights said.
Troops shot and wounded five protesters in the capital and 20 in the central 
  town of Helfaya, where two civilians also died, while another demonstrator 
  was killed in the northern city of Aleppo, the Britain-based Observatory 
Aleppo-based activist Mohammed al-Halabi said the protester died from his 
  wounds after regime forces opened fire in the Salaheddine neighbourhood.
All but one of those killed on Friday were civilians, with one soldier killed 
  and six others wounded in Jisr al-Shugur city in Idlib province when a blast 
State television, meanwhile, said troops killed a would-be suicide bomber in 
"The Syrian authorities have foiled an attempted suicide attack in 
  Al-Shaar area in Aleppo, and killed the would-be attacker," the channel 
  added, saying the attacker's car was laden with 2,640 pounds of explosives.
Anti-regime activists dismissed the official account of a foiled attack as "a 
  lie," according to Mr Halabi.
"It is not in the interests of the (rebel) Free Syrian Army to stage 
  attacks on a Friday," the day of weekly mass anti-regime protests over 
  the past 14 months, Mr Halabi said.
Thursday's bomb attacks in the capital were the deadliest in 14 months of 
  unrest, killing 55 people and wounding nearly 400, to a chorus of 
  international condemnation.
The United Nations called on both sides in the conflict to co-operate with a 
  month-old ceasefire as President Bashar al-Assad's regime and the opposition 
  traded accusations over the perpetrators of the carnage.
More than 12,000 people, the majority of them civilians, have died since the 
  uprising began, according to the Observatory, including more than 900 killed 
  since the April 12 truce went into effect.
&amp;pound;5 billion budget for special needs pupils rising fast, but Peter 
  Stanford asks is it tackling poor teachers and parents?
Featured Advertising
Search for a property
MORE FROM TELEGRAPH.CO.UK
&amp;copy; Copyright of Telegraph Media Group Limited 2012
Terms and Conditions
</text>
</article>