<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>12670</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/independent-ie-a2c58f6ea375592bd492af7e870f91f4.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1086</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/19/2012 1:06:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Explore news, videos, and much more based on what your friends are reading and watching. Publish your own activity and retain full control.
Defendant Anders Behring Breivik &amp;hellip;
Defendant Anders Behring Breivik &amp;hellip;
Prosecutors Svein Holden, left, &amp;hellip;
OSLO, Norway (AP) — Confessed mass killer Anders Behring Breivik's original plans for a terror attack was to bomb Oslo's government district, the Labor Party's office and a third target, possibly the royal palace, he told a court Thursday.
The far-right fanatic has confessed to setting off a car bomb outside the government headquarters on July 22, and then opening fire at a Labor Party youth camp outside the capital. A total of 77 people were killed in Norway's worst peacetime massacre.
Questioned by prosecutors, Breivik said his original plan was to build three bombs. One would be placed at the government district and the second at the office of the governing Labor Party.
He had several options for the third target.
"I settled on the palace in a setting where the royal family wouldn't be hurt," he said. "Most nationalists and cultural conservatives are supporters of the monarchy, including myself."
Breivik said the three bombs would be followed by several shooting massacres, if he survived. He decided against multiple bombs because building one was "much more difficult than I thought."
"When I reached a situation where it was impossible to make more than one bomb, it resulted in a strategy of one bomb and one shooting-based action," he said.
His preferred targets for the shooting massacre was an annual conference of Norwegian journalists or the Labor Party's annual meeting. But he couldn't get prepared in time, so he decided on striking against the summer retreat of the Labor Party's youth wing.
The 33-year-old Norwegian said he had expected to be confronted by armed police when he left Oslo for Utoya island. He killed 69 people there, armed with a handgun and a rifle — both named after Norse gods.
"I estimated the chances of survival as less than 5 percent," he said.
Breivik, who styles himself as a modern-day crusader, has confessed to the attacks but rejects criminal guilt, saying he was acting to protect Norway and Europe by targeting left-wing political forces he claims have betrayed the country by opening it up to immigration.
"Militant nationalists are split in two," Breivik said Thursday. "One half says you should attack Muslims and minorities. The other half says you should attack elites, those who are responsible."
The key issue of the trial is to establish whether he is criminally insane.
He entered the Oslo district court without the clenched-fist salute he had used in previous hearings.
In his testimony, Breivik said he played the computer game "Modern Warfare" for 16 months starting in January 2010, primarily to get a feel for how to use rifle sights.
Breivik said he decided already in 2006 to carry out what he expected to be a "suicide" operation. First he took a "sabbatical year" fully devoted to play another computer game, "World of Warcraft," for 16 hours a day.
Breivik said that cutting off social contact for a full year helped him prepare for the attacks, but the game-playing was "pure entertainment. It doesn't have anything to do with July 22."
Prosecutors challenged Breivik's assertion that he decided on an attack already in 2006, noting that his preparations for the attacks started in 2009, when he created an agricultural firm to buy chemicals for explosives.
Showing no sign of remorse, Breivik calmly answers questions from prosecutors, except when they ask about the alleged anti-Muslim "Knights Templar" network he claims to belong to. Prosecutors say they don't believe it exists.
When he smiled at one point during questioning Wednesday, Prosecutor Svein Holden asked him how he thought the bereaved watching the proceedings in court would react to that.
"They probably react in a natural way, with horror and disgust," Breivik said. He said he smiled because he knew where Holden was going with his line of questioning.
The main point of his defense is to avoid an insanity ruling, which would deflate his political arguments. He repeatedly accuses prosecutors of trying to "ridicule" him by highlighting portions of a rambling, 1,500-page manifesto he posted before the attacks.
In it — and in a shortened version he read to the court on Tuesday — he said the "Knights Templar" will lead a revolt against "multiculturalist" governments around Europe, with the aim of deporting Muslims.
If found sane, Breivik could face a maximum 21-year prison sentence or an alternate custody arrangement that would keep him locked up as long as he is considered a menace to society. If declared insane, he would be committed to psychiatric care for as long as he's considered ill.
The trial is expected to last 10 weeks.
Associated Press Writer Bjoern H. Amland in Oslo, Norway contributed to this report
Accused Norwegian Anders Behring Breivik &amp;hellip;
Norway killer thought he had only a &amp;hellip;
Breivik thought had slim chance to survive &amp;hellip;
Lay judge dismissed in Breivik case
How long to keep your tax returns
Dog wars heat up the presidential race
Actor unrecognizable as Hitchcock
TV legend Dick Clark dies at 82
UNITED NATIONS/PARIS (Reuters) - Syria has not fully withdrawn troops and heavy weapons from towns, failing to send a "clear signal" about its commitment to peace, U.N. chief Ban Ki-moon said on Thursday, &amp;hellip; More »U.N. head says Syria yet to send clear signal on peace
UNITED NATIONS/PARIS (Reuters) - Syria has not fully withdrawn troops and heavy weapons from towns, failing to send a "clear signal" about its commitment to peace, U.N. chief Ban Ki-moon said on Thursday, underlining Western fears for the week-old truce. In the first progress report since the Security Council passed a resolution &amp;hellip;
BHUBANESWAR, India (Reuters) - India successfully test-fired on Thursday a nuclear-capable missile that can reach Beijing and Eastern Europe, thrusting the emerging Asian power into a small club of nations &amp;hellip; More »India tests nuclear-capable missile that can reach China
BHUBANESWAR, India (Reuters) - India successfully test-fired on Thursday a nuclear-capable missile that can reach Beijing and Eastern Europe, thrusting the emerging Asian power into a small club of nations that can deploy nuclear weapons at such a great distance. Footage showed the rocket with a range of more than 5,000 &amp;hellip;
BAGHDAD (Reuters) - More than 20 bombs hit cities and towns across Iraq on Thursday, killing at least 36 and wounding more than 100, police and hospital sources said, raising fears of sectarian strife &amp;hellip; More »At least 36 killed in wave of Iraq blasts
BAGHDAD (Reuters) - More than 20 bombs hit cities and towns across Iraq on Thursday, killing at least 36 and wounding more than 100, police and hospital sources said, raising fears of sectarian strife in a country keen to show it can now maintain security. In Baghdad, three car bombs, two roadside bombs and one suicide &amp;hellip;
YANGON (Reuters) - Aung San Suu Kyi's planned debut in Myanmar's parliament next week could be shelved amid a standoff between her party and the government over one word used in the swearing-in oath for &amp;hellip; More »Myanmar oath standoff puts Suu Kyi's MP debut in doubt
YANGON (Reuters) - Aung San Suu Kyi's planned debut in Myanmar's parliament next week could be shelved amid a standoff between her party and the government over one word used in the swearing-in oath for new lawmakers. Newly elected MPs from Suu Kyi's National League for Democracy (NLD) party see the oath in its present &amp;hellip;
LONDON (Reuters) - British legislators said on Thursday they hoped to publish on May 1 a long-awaited report into a phone hacking scandal centered on News Corp's now-closed News of the World tabloid. Parliament's &amp;hellip; More »UK parliament aims to publish hacking report on May 1
LONDON (Reuters) - British legislators said on Thursday they hoped to publish on May 1 a long-awaited report into a phone hacking scandal centered on News Corp's now-closed News of the World tabloid. Parliament's culture committee is widely expected to criticize News Corp in the report, raising the possibility that the &amp;hellip;
Get breaking news, videos, blogs and more at ABC News. More »Breaking News from ABC News
Credit card companies offer huge bonuses. More »If you have stellar credit
These flexible online degrees could help you go to school on your terms.
Thinking about going back to school? Find out which online degrees rank highest in popularity.
</text>
</article>