<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>7123</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/aljazeera-en-3dc5a8f9c0cfd58e6c71e7af58950f87.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g49</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/10/2012 5:04:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>KABUL, April 10 (Xinhua) -- Twin suicide car bombs rocked the western Herat and southern Helmand provinces in Afghanistan on Tuesday, killing 19 people including 5 attackers and injuring 35 others, officials confirmed.
Qari Yusuf Ahmadi, a self-proclaimed Taliban spokesman, claimed responsibility for the twin suicide bombings, saying that Taliban loyalists killed 23 policemen in the attacks.
The first car bombing occurred in front of the entrance of government building of Guzara district in Herat province at about 8:45 a.m. local time when dozens of people lined up to enter the building and meet the officials," district governor Nisar Ahmad Popul, who escaped the attack, told Xinhua.
"A total of 12 people including two suicide bombers were killed and 30 others injured in the suicide car bomb attack this morning in Guzara district," provincial police chief Seyd Agha Saqib told Xinhua.
In addition to the two bombers, six civilians including a woman and four policemen were also killed, Saqib said.
Hours later, the second suicide attack struck a police station in former Taliban stronghold Helmand province, killing four police and wounding five others.
"Three suicide bombers driving an explosive-laden car raided police headquarters in Mosa Qala district at 11:00 a.m. today where four police were martyred and five others sustained injuries including police chief Abdul Wali Koka," said a press release issued by Helmand provincial administration.
Meanwhile, spokesman for provincial administration Daud Ahmadi told Xinhua that two suicide bombers who attempted to sneak into police headquarters were stopped by police before blowing themselves up inside the car, causing casualties around.
He added that another suicide bomber was shot dead in the building by police.
The twin suicide bombings came just two days after the top U.S. commander in Afghanistan General John Allen and Afghan Defense Minister Abdul Rahim Wardak signe a deal, allowing Afghan security forces to take the lead in special operations including the controversial night raids.
Citing Afghan security forces' poor equipment, many Afghans worry that Taliban militants who often hide among civilians may benefit from halting night raids by NATO-led forces.
Brushing aside the concerns, Afghan Defense Ministry spokesman Zahir Azimi told reporters Tuesday: "The Afghan Special Operations Unit is capable and well equipped to carry out all special operations in war against insurgents."
Special Report: Afghanistan Situation
</text>
</article>