<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>31353</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/news-yahoo-cfc81eb5c2428885b16e5fbb0782a8d4.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g304</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/27/2012 3:51:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>At the end of seven-nation talks in Baghdad, the game of high-stakes poker over Iran's nuclear program is set to go another round. Positions have been staked out ahead of the next meeting slated for mid-June in Moscow. (26.05.2012) 
German engineers began construction on that plant in the 1975 before the Islamic Revolution brought the Ayatollah regime to power four years later. Russia subsequently finished the plant, which as inaugurated in 2010, and continues to help maintain and provide fuel for the facility.
Abbasi Davani was quoted by INSA as saying that the plans for a new 360-megawatt plant at Darkhovin, near Bushehr, "have been finished and we are reviewing it."
The announcement was made three days after negotiations in Baghdad between Iran and six world powers - China, France, Germany, Russia the US and the UK - failed to produce results. They agreed to meet again in Moscow on June 18-19.
"Evils from all directions"
Iranian President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad addressed parliament for the first time since two rounds of national elections in March and May, in which hardliners loyal to Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khameini trounced Ahmadinejad 's loyalists.
The president lost support partially due to the perception that he was trying to challenge the Khameini's power. Under the Islamic Republic's constitution, the Supreme Leader has the final say on all national issues.
"Today, evils have been mobilized from all directions to put the Iranian nation under pressure. Removing and resisting the pressures, and cooperation, are the main priority today," Ahmadinejad told lawmakers without elaborating. State TV broadcast the speech live.
Western nations accuse Iran of seeking to build a nuclear weapon and have imposed crushing sanctions against the Islamic Republic's oil exports and banking sector.  The United States and Israel have threatened to use military force if Iran doesn't open its program to inspectors and to stop high-level uranium enrichment.
Tehran claims that its atomic program is peaceful and wants the sanctions to be loosened in exchange for possible concessions.
Tehran plans to build two additional nuclear power plants in the coming years despite suspicion by Western powers. The Iranian president has told parliament that the country is surrounded by "evils."
Deposed Egyptian strongman Hosni Mubarak's top aide has been sentenced to seven years in prison on charges of corruption. The sentence comes a week before Mubarak faces his own day in court.
The main rebel group in Syria has said that it will not respect the cease-fire agreement if the UN doesn't act to protect civilians. The Syrian government, meanwhile, has blamed the massacre in Houla on terrorists.
A NATO airstrike has killed eight members of a family in eastern Afghanistan, authorities there said on Sunday. The father of the family apparently had no connection to the Taliban.
</text>
</article>