<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>27317</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/alertnet-f38811d5692891a2cba6ffb6a33bf29e.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g237</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/23/2012 11:51:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Welcome back,   (log out?)
The chief of the UN nuclear agency says he has reached a deal with Iran over probing suspected work on nuclear weapons, and adds that the agreement will be "signed quite soon."
Iran has been under sanctions for 33 years. The most recent round targeted not only oil export, bank transfers and researcher visas, but also food and consumer goods. Young Iranians say the measures are even affecting their chances of tying the knot.
The Pentagon has a ready plan for a military attack on Iran, the American ambassador to Israel warned days before a key meeting over the controversial nuclear program of the Islamic Republic.
Published: 23 May, 2012, 13:47
An Israeli fighter jet (Reuters/Jerry Lampen)
A military strike against Iranian facilities is not out of the question, even though Tehran has reached agreement on a probe with the UN’s nuclear watchdog, says Israeli Defense Minister Ehud Barak.
­The official was referring to a deal announced on Tuesday by the International Atomic Energy Agency. Barak called it an Iranian ploy to fend off international pressure.
The minister told Army Radio that "a nuclear Iran is intolerable and no options should be taken off the table," referring to the use of force.
He said the only way Israel could see Iran develop its civilian nuclear industry is if it shuts down all of its uranium enrichment sites and uses imported fuel.
The comments came as Iranian nuclear negotiators are meeting the P5+1 group in Baghdad on Wednesday. They are to discuss the conflict over Iran’s nuclear ambitions, which the West suspects of being a clandestine attempt to build an atomic weapon. Iran insists its pursuits are purely civilian.
"Dragging things out, in our eyes, is problematic, so conversations between the West and Iran must occur more frequently. North Korea also negotiated with the West but in the end tested nuclear weapons," Barak pointed out.
Last week US Ambassador Dan Shapiro said the Pentagon has a plan for a military strike on Iran, and may carry it out if ordered.
"It would be preferable to resolve this diplomatically and through the use of pressure than to use military force," he said.
Possible use of force against Iran has been discussed by Israel and its western allies for months. Israel insists on the right to strike when and if it sees fit, saying it will not ask for anyone’s consent. There is fear that if such an attack happens, Iran would retaliate at any forces it sees as enemies, which could result in a major regional war.
War mentality has saturated Washington and arms merchants want to benefit, says Congressman (d) Dennis Kucinich. He opposes sanctions against Tehran that could lead to war, and is sure the US should forget about trying to conquer other countries.
I am sure the Nazis were prosecuted for starting an unjust and agressive war. If that is so how far off of the mark was George Orwells Animal Farm.
quite arrogant of Israel, to behave as if Iran was Poland, and we shall bomb you the experimental state says. however the problem is that next is Russia. and moreover, sense 1776 there have being wars, for useless reasons, just now from Afghanistan, Iraq, Libya Syria, Iran, you can perceive the trend, it is obvious next is china and Russia.
outside israel who really believes this man (barak)? Israel officials have lost their crediblity long ago.
        &amp;copy; Autonomous Nonprofit Organization "TV-Novosti", 2005-2012. All rights reserved.
</text>
</article>