<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>5151</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/hurriyetdailynews-39dc718a78ea334f8bb98ca04f2305df.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g797</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/4/2012 6:40:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Afghan policemen inspect the site of a suicide attack in Maymana, the capital of Faryab province, north of Kabul on April 4, 2012. PHOTO: AFP
MAZAR-I-SHARIF, AFGHANISTAN: A suicide bomber attacked foreign military forces in northern Afghanistan on Wednesday, killing at least 12 people including three international troops, officials said.
Video footage from the scene showed a number of foreign troops lying immobile on the ground in the aftermath of the blast, while blood-soaked civilian and military victims writhed in pain from savage wounds including severed limbs.
There were conflicting reports about the exact death toll and the identity of the victims after the suicide bomber, who police said was riding an explosives-packed motorcycle, blew himself up.
No Norwegian ISAF personnel were nearby at the time, he added.
But relations between the allies have been strained this year by a series of killings of Western troops by Afghan security personnel, a massacre of 17 civilians blamed on a US soldier and the burning of Korans at a US base.
Night raids by special forces against insurgent hideouts have also triggered popular anger and long been a source of friction with Karzai, who has denounced the NATO operations as reckless.
But US officials said Tuesday Washington and Kabul were close to an agreement giving Afghans more authority over the raids, with Afghan judges issuing warrants for the operations and Afghans in the lead on the ground.
Such a deal could remove the last obstacle to final negotiations on a long-term security agreement, which US officials hope to ink in time for a NATO summit in May in Chicago.
The Faryab attack came as the number of NATO troops killed in Afghanistan so far this year passed 100, according to an AFP count based on the independent icasualties.org website.
The war has cost the West hundreds of billions of dollars and almost 3,000 lives so far. The United States has suffered the most deaths at 1,924, according to icasualties, with Britain next on 407.
ISAF declined to confirm the total figure for 2012 so far, but according to icasualties it is slightly lower than in 2011, when 109 troops had been killed by the end of March.
ISAF spokesman Lieutenant Colonel Jimmie Cummings said that across Afghanistan, insurgent attacks fell by nine percent in 2011 and in January and February they were down 22 percent.
</text>
</article>