<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>26157</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/jrep-1e46682e448cf4b13b13349979cfe256.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g721</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/22/2012 9:44:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Welcome back,   (log out?)
A suicide car bomb explosion has ripped through a military compound in the Syrian city of Deir el-Zour, killing nine people and injuring 100. It is the latest in a string of blasts targeting regime military facilities in the embattled country.
Admitting that the chances for negotiations between the Syrian authorities and the political opposition remain slim, Russia’s Deputy Foreign Minister added that the world’s premier terrorist group is responsible for wreaking havoc in the Arab Republic.
A major blast is reported to have ripped through Aleppo, Syria’s largest city. The bomb allegedly targeted the headquarters of Syria’s ruling Ba'ath Party.
Syrian forces have foiled a major terror plot just a day after twin blasts killed 56 and injured hundreds more in Damascus. The authorities are calling on the UN, saying the country has become a hotbed of terrorism supported from abroad.
At least 55 people have been killed and 372 others injured by two powerful blasts in the Syrian capital on Thursday morning. The car bombs detonated near a military intelligence building.
Published: 22 May, 2012, 11:22
A handout picture from the Syrian Arab News Agency (SANA) shows Syrian men carrying away a corpse at the site of twin blasts in Damascus on May 10, 2012 (AFP Photo/HO/SANA)
An explosion in a restaurant in the Syrian capital has killed five people, Syrian state media report. The blast struck the Qaboun district of Damascus and has been branded a “terrorist” attack.
The Assad government uses this term when referring to members of Syrian opposition groups.
The neighborhood has been the site of several protests demanding the ouster of Syrian president Bashar al-Assad.
The UK-based rights group the Syrian Observatory for Human Rights said the bomb went off just after midnight, but gave no information as to who was behind the attack.
The blast is the latest in a series of explosions that have rocked the embattled country over the last couple of weeks. On Saturday a suicide bomb ripped through the parking lot of a security compound in the eastern city of Deir el-Zour, killing nine people and injuring 100.
The Assad government said the boms blasts were also orchestrated by terrorists.
Twin suicide bomb attacks struck Damascus on May 10, claiming 55 lives and injuring hundreds. UN Secretary General Ban Ki-moon condemned the violence, saying he believed Al Qaeda must be behind the blasts.
Uprisings against President Assad begun fourteen months ago and have become increasingly militarized and violent over the past months, in spite of the ceasefire imposed by the UN.
UN monitors are currently stationed in the country to oversee a joint Arab League-UN brokered peace plan.
A South African politician bought a painting with state funds by disguising it as a purchase of 256 Big Mac burger meals.
The chief of the UN nuclear agency says he has reached a deal with Iran over probing suspected work on nuclear weapons, and adds that the agreement will be "signed quite soon."
Funny how in Western media, they don't talk much of these attacks.But when the Syrian government gets involved in a activity. They pin them like a tail on a donkey.
The Western media refers to those behind this kind of attacks in Syria as 'ACTIVISTS' meaning 'people actively involved in terror against the Syrian nation'. I see in some writeups that RT still refers to the Syrian legitimate Govt as 'Assad Regime' following the trend of the MSM. RT should understand that some of these terminologies are normally used against Govts that have refused to be puppets to the Western leaders and RT should be smart enough to coin their own tags just like the Americans will not refer to their Govt as Obama Regime rather they will say Obama Administration, why would RT not also use the term 'Assad Administration'?Do we now start calling the Russian Govt as PUTIN REGIME? Please show some respect to the suffering Syrian people being destroyed by foreign 'Friends of Syria' sponsored terror groups.
@ RT " a “terrorist” attack.
The Assad government uses this term when referring to members of Syrian opposition groups."RT,  Seriously, what else would you call a TERRORIST attack but that what it is - a TERRORIST ATTACK.  Are you so intimidated by the Zionist, Khazar "Jews" that you find it difficult to express the TRUTH. I know that you're under immense pressure, especially in the Khazar "Jew" controlled USA, but we all have an obligation to TRUTH and JUSTICE - no matter the consequences.
        &amp;copy; Autonomous Nonprofit Organization "TV-Novosti", 2005-2012. All rights reserved.
</text>
</article>