<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>1575</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/news-yahoo-fe8138b9f1da91b515ba71c6d3a6c137.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1029</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>12/6/2011 10:40:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>      December 06, 2011 21:34:53
Twin blasts at shrines on the Shiite holy day of Ashura have left at least 34 people dead in cities across Afghanistan.
A massive blast at the entrance to a shrine in central Kabul where Shiite Muslims had gathered to mark Ashura left at least 30 people dead including children, an AFP photographer said.
"A suicide bomber detonated his explosives in the Abu-Ul Fazil shrine," Kabul police said in a statement.
A security official speaking on condition of anonymity told AFP that it was believed the bomber arrived with a group of Shiite pilgrims from Logar province, south of Kabul.
In a second attack, four people were killed in Mazar-i-Sharif when a blast struck a shrine in the northern city. It was not immediately clear whether Shiites were targeted in that attack.
"It was an explosion not a suicide bombing. It was some explosives hidden in a bicycle," said Lal Mohammad Ahmadzai, a police spokesman for northern Afghanistan.
He added that four other people had also been injured.
Shiites were banned from marking Ashura in public under the Taliban who ruled Afghanistan until 2001. This year, there are more Ashura monuments around the city than usual including black shrines and flags.
The 10-day Ashura ceremonies, which began on November 27 but peak on Tuesday, mark the slaughter of Imam Hussein, the grandson of the Prophet Mohammed, near Karbala by armies of the caliph Yazid in 680 AD.
There was no immediate claim of responsibility for either of the blasts from the Taliban or other insurgent groups operating in Afghanistan.
Afghan president Hamid Karzai has condemned the attacks as "horrible terrorism".
"The terrorists actions today in Kabul and also in Mazar-i-Sharif is the first time that on such an important religious day in Afghanistan terrorism of that horrible nature is taking place," he said.
The attacks came shortly after a major conference on Afghanistan's future, held in the German city of Bonn, 10 years after talks there put in place an interim government after US-led troops ousted the Taliban.
However, Pakistan and the Taliban - both seen as pivotal to any end to the bloody strife in Afghanistan - decided to stay away from the talks, undermining already modest hopes for real progress.
</text>
</article>