<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>10451</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/jpost-f709c08ad161612e435b94110761664a.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g571</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/15/2012 1:00:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Rockets fired at parliament building and embassies in apparently co-ordinated assault on government and diplomatic areas
Activist, Wazhma Frogh, of the Afghan Women's Network says she has just dogged a bullet
missed a bullet outside health ministry. roads blocked women n kids running on the road.
&amp;mdash; Wazhma (@FroghWazhma) April 15, 2012
Pictures arriving from the scene in Kabul. This shows both the police and army are now on the streets.
Associated Press reports that the attacks are focused in three diplomatic neighbourhoods in Kabul:
Militants launched a series of coordinated attacks in the Afghan capital Sunday, with blasts and gunfire rocking three neighborhoods that are home to Afghan government buildings, Western embassies and NATO bases.
The attacks were the first in the heavily guarded capital since a shooting inside the Interior Ministry in February in which a ministry employee turned a gun on NATO advisers and shot two soldiers dead.
More than 10 explosions in all rocked the capital Sunday, and heavy gunfire shook the city for more than an hour after the initial blast. There were no immediate reports of casualties.
Amie Ferris-Rotman, a Reuters correspondent in Kabul is tweeting live from the scene. It seems the surrounding area of her office in Wazir Akbar Khan, where their office is based, is under sustained attack
More gunfire crackling right near Reuters office in Kabul
— Amie Ferris-Rotman (@Amiefr_Reuters) April 15, 2012
Second explosion heard right near Reuters office in Kabul
— Amie Ferris-Rotman (@Amiefr_Reuters) April 15, 2012
Woah. Our entire office just rumbled
— Amie Ferris-Rotman (@Amiefr_Reuters) April 15, 2012
That's 14 large explosions so far in coordinated attack in Kabul
— Amie Ferris-Rotman (@Amiefr_Reuters) April 15, 2012
@joelvanhoudt we are sitting at our desks in flaks
— Amie Ferris-Rotman (@Amiefr_Reuters) April 15, 2012
— Amie Ferris-Rotman (@Amiefr_Reuters) April 15, 2012
— Amie Ferris-Rotman (@Amiefr_Reuters) April 15, 2012
— Amie Ferris-Rotman (@Amiefr_Reuters) April 15, 2012
He said a group of armed suicide bombers launched an attack on the NATO forces headquarters, the parliament building across town and a number of diplomatic residences in Kabul.
Last week, Mujahid said in a statement that Taliban planners were preparing to launch a spring offensive. In a statement posted on a Taliban website on Thursday, he said NATO officials should have patience, because Taliban commanders would wait for the "appropriate time" to launch attacks.
Emma Graham-Harrison tells us the attacks are widespread.
Insurgents also attacked the provincial governor's headquarters and the Nato military base in Logar province south of Kabul. In eastern Jalalabad city the airport, also a Nato military base, was targeted by suicide bombers.
The Taliban claimed responsibility for the attacks, the first major assault of the year. An Interior Ministry employee with security clearance in February shot dead two Nato advisers working there.
"A big number of soldiers went to do a spring season operation, that started today in Kabul. The headquarters of ISAF, the NDS office, and the British embassy are under attack," spokesman Zabihullah Mujuahid said.
"They have suicide vests, heavy weapons like RPG, and hand grenades and assault rifles."
A spokesman for the Nato-led coalition said Afghan and foreign forces were responding to attacks in several locations around Kabul but declined further comment.
Aminullah Amini, head of the media department of parliament has told reporters what he saw.
"I saw 7 or 8 rockets fired towards parliament, none of them hit the building, they landed on the streets around. One was near a man on a bike, and he was thrown to the ground and didn't move," he said.
"I ran away from the building with several colleagues when the attack started, but many members of parliament are still inside," Amini added.
Dispatch from our Kabul correspondent Emma Graham-Harrison just in. She describes the chaos currently unfolding in the diplomatic area of Kabul.
The Taliban fired rockets at the Afghan parliament and into the heart of the capital's diplomatic district as part of an ambitious nationwide "spring assault" on government and foreign military and diplomatic headquarters.
Several attackers took over a multi-storey hotel on the edge of Kabul's diplomatic district, and used it to attack nearby embassies and foreign military headquarters in the heavily fortified area known locally as the "green zone".
Smoke billowed from buildings apparently inside embassy and military compounds, among them a British diplomatic residence, a Reuters' witness reported. An eyewitness saw three bodies in a pickup truck a block away from the attack.
In the west of the city insurgents targeted the legislature, and heavy and light machine gunfire echoed through the deserted streets, with students at a nearby university in lockdown.
Just spoken to the FCO. They will not confirm that there has been a hit on British diplomatic residence. A spokeswoman said:
"We can confirm that there in an ongoing incident in the diplomatic area of Kabul.  We are in close contact with Embassy staff."
11.40am: A series of explosions followed by sustained gunfire have shaken the Afghan capital Kabul in what appears to be a co-ordinated attack on two areas frequented by Afghan government officials and their international allies.
The first blasts struck the Wazir Akbar Khan area of central Kabul, home to a number of embassies and a Nato base. Gunfire broke out soon after, forcing people into the street to take cover. Smoke could be seen rising from a few buildings as sirens wailed. Heavy gunfire continued more than 30 minutes after the initial explosion.
The Taliban said they and other militant groups were behind a coordinated assault in the Afghan capital, Kabul, on Sunday which included attacks on the British and German embassies in the heavily guarded, central diplomatic district. The Taliban also said they were carrying out attacks in several Afghan provinces. We'll bring you full coverage as the situation develops.
11.40am: A series of explosions followed by sustained gunfire have shaken the Afghan capital Kabul in what appears to be a co-ordinated attack on two areas frequented by Afghan government officials and their international allies.
The first blasts struck the Wazir Akbar Khan area of central Kabul, home to a number of embassies and a Nato base. Gunfire broke out soon after, forcing people into the street to take cover. Smoke could be seen rising from a few buildings as sirens wailed. Heavy gunfire continued more than 30 minutes after the initial explosion.
The Taliban said they and other militant groups were behind a coordinated assault in the Afghan capital, Kabul, on Sunday which included attacks on the British and German embassies in the heavily guarded, central diplomatic district. The Taliban also said they were carrying out attacks in several Afghan provinces. We'll bring you full coverage as the situation develops.
More from News blog on
More 			minute by minutes
Explosions and gunfire rock Kabul
US embassy in Kabul attacked - video
US embassy in Kabul under attack – Tuesday 13 September 2011
Kabul attack: 'An ambulance was rigged up as a suicide bomb'
15 comments, displaying  first
Show comments in new window
15 April 2012 11:56AM
Nothing is being achieved other than innocent people suffering more loss. Time to pull the troops out.
Get the armies out and spend the same money on rebuilding the country and education and the infrastructure.
15 April 2012 11:57AM
Out with the puppet regime! Out with NATO/yanks! We want Najibullah, or, rather, his successors!
15 April 2012 12:06PM
Yes. It's happening again - but why Afghan "security forces" never learn anything? They have been attacked from the surounding mountains in similar fashion before - why they can't/don't secure those mountains.
It seems like - NATO leave today - come in the Taliban tomorrow.
15 April 2012 12:09PM
Why do supposedly peace loving Muslims keep blowing people up ,in most cases other members of their own creed.and yet expousing that Islam is the religion of peace.
15 April 2012 12:09PM
Nothing is being achieved other than innocent people suffering more loss. Time to pull the troops out.
Get the armies out and spend the same money on rebuilding the country and education and the infrastructure.
Only the people trying to rebuild the country will be squealing  for somebody to protect them from the bearded savages trying to rip their heads off.
15 April 2012 12:10PM
We should take the gloves off and be as brutal as we need to be to clear out Afghanistan. What is the point of having nuclear weapons and other advanced weaponry if we don't use it to clean out the rats from the mountains and from Pakistan. We were stupid enough to kick the Soviets out. They would have done a better job without the hand wringing from our media.
15 April 2012 12:11PM
I'm surprised to see a comments box open under this report. Any one in the green zone reading this?
15 April 2012 12:13PM
Comments?!  This is news not opinion.  Don't let tragedy of this scale become an opportunity for spleen-venting!
15 April 2012 12:16PM
NATO can best achieve its objectives by withdrawing ground forces and providing air support for the Northern Alliance in the ensuing civil war.  Use airfields in the former Soviet republics north of Afghanistan.
Also, spray the poppy fields except in NA-held areas.
15 April 2012 12:19PM
Why do supposedly peace loving Muslims keep blowing people up ,in most cases other members of their own creed.and yet expousing that Islam is the religion of peace.
The fact that you have no problem so smarmily and nastily judging the religion followed by more than one billion people by the despicable actions of a few says far more about you than it does about Islam.
Very sad occurrence in Kabul, by the way.
15 April 2012 12:21PM
Agreed. Afghanistan is heading towards a war of attrition between the Taliban and the Northern Alliance.  Any attempt to resurrect Islamist training camps is likely to be dealt with from a drone or the weapon racks of an aircraft.
15 April 2012 12:22PM
The fact that you have no problem so smarmily and nastily judging the religion followed by more than one billion people by the despicable actions of a few says far more about you than it does about Islam
If fun loving beardies butcher in the name of their religion, people have carte blanche to judge said religion - whether Guardianistas like it or not
15 April 2012 12:24PM
Where are You sitting mate?Surely, you would not like that done to your country.I do not agree with violence though.I think mad US service men should stop killing women and children twenty at a time,and the Taliban should leave their bombs and AK 47s at home so the the benefactors of Afghanistancan withdraw "peacefully" after everything is demolished and there is nothing else to bomb.
15 April 2012 12:25PM
The five-star general's lament
In Kabul-town, upon the stair, I met a Taliban,who wasn't thereHe wasn't there again today I wish to God he'd go away...
15 April 2012 12:28PM
think mad US service men should stop killing women and children twenty at a time,and the Taliban should leave their bombs and AK 47s at home so the the benefactors of Afghanistan
Once NATO goes you guardianistas will see killing  and savagery on the grandest of scales as Afghanistan resorts to the 12thc.
Zeitgeist is an experiment in showing trending news, topics and articles from the Guardian. Find out more in our blog post.
Follow all the top stories of the day on Twitter with the Guardian's world news team
guardianworld: RT @ReutersIndia: U.S. embassy in Kabul says "attacks are ongoing in the vicinity of the embassy"
Jon_Boone: Good to see @bsarwary doing some good poolside reporting at the Beeb's Kabul bureau.
Search the Guardian bookshop
</text>
</article>