<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>10612</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/jpost-f709c08ad161612e435b94110761664a.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g571</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/15/2012 8:54:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Dow Jones Reprints: This copy is for your personal, non-commercial use only. To order presentation-ready copies for distribution to your colleagues, clients or customers, use the Order Reprints tool at the bottom of any article or visit
The attacks on foreign embassies, Parliament and military bases in Kabul unfolded in rapid succession, halting normal life in the city. Gunfire and explosions, which emptied the streets during a normally busy workday, continued into the night.
The coordinated violence in Kabul and the eastern cities of Gardez, Jalalabad and Pul-i-Alam, marked the first significant salvo from the Taliban insurgency this year as it tries to derail American plans to transfer responsibility for protecting the country to Afghan forces over the next two years.
Gunmen launch multiple attacks in the Afghan capital Kabul, assaulting Western embassies and the parliament. Video: Reuters/Photo: Getty Images
"This is our new tactic and is indicative of our strength," said Taliban spokesman Zabihullah Mujahid. "These attacks show that we are capable of launching major attacks and also show that there is cooperation with us from inside the government."
While the Taliban took responsibility for Sunday's violence, Western officials in Kabul said the coordinated strikes were most likely the work of the Haqqani network, an autonomous part of the Taliban movement that has been accused of staging the most devastating attacks on the Afghan capital in recent years.
"My guess, based on previous experience here is that this was [the] Haqqani network operation out of North Waziristan and Pakistan tribal areas," U.S. Ambassador Ryan Crocker said on CNN.
While the attacks appeared to fall short of delivering significant casualties, they may have succeeded in sending a message that the insurgency can still strike in the very heart of the country, said Martine van Biljert, co-director of the Afghanistan Analysts Network, an independent Kabul-based think tank.
"It's really aimed at the war of perceptions," she said. "You try to start the fighting season with a bang and wipe away the claims that the Taliban haven't been able to pull off their major offensive. It's much more symbolic than tactical."
Two Afghan police officers were killed and at least 14 were injured during the attacks, Afghan officials said, along with 27 Afghan civilians injured. At least two Afghan university students were killed as the U.S.-led coalition responded to the Taliban assault in Gardez, local residents said.
Yusaf Khan, a Paktia University student who said he witnessed the airstrikes, said 28 Afghan civilians, including women and children, were wounded in the coalition attack. A spokesman for the U.S.-led military coalition said  there were no reports of civilian casualties caused by the airstrikes.
The Afghan government said at least 17 insurgents were killed and a dozen  suspects were captured on Sunday. Most of the fighting in Kabul was done by the Afghan troops.
U.S. officials hailed the response of Afghan security forces, describing the outcome of the fighting as a sign of progress.
"I am enormously proud of how quickly Afghan security forces responded to today's attacks in Kabul," said U.S. Marine Gen. John Allen, the coalition commander. "They were on scene immediately, well-led and well-coordinated. They integrated their efforts, helped protect their fellow citizens and largely kept the insurgents contained."
Not all the Afghans, however, saw the Afghan response as a success, especially as much of the capital city remained paralyzed by the violence.
Wazhma Frogh, a women's activist and executive director of a new think tank called the Research Institute for Women, Peace and Security, said Afghan police recklessly fired over the heads of civilians to disperse people in the early minutes of the attack.
"I could feel the heat, the fire of the bullets whizzing over my head," said Ms. Frogh, who heard Afghan police officers at checkpoints joking about where to hide as the attack intensified. "Is this what transition is all about?" she asked.
While U.S. officials praised the Afghan response, President Hamid Karzai made no public appearances and issued no statements about the pitched battle that raged in Kabul.
As the first sounds of explosions ripped through the capital early on Sunday, Afghans rushed for shelter and the U.S. Embassy's "duck and cover" alarm echoed through the diplomatic neighborhood that appeared to be the hardest hit.
Insurgents armed with suicide vests, rocket-propelled grenades and heavy machine guns commandeered high-rise construction sites in three locations across the capital.
As the militants stormed the Kabul buildings, insurgents in three other provinces staged near-simultaneous attacks on U.S. military bases and Afghan government compounds.
The most serious attack in the capital targeted the city's diplomatic quarter, where militants commandeered an unfinished, seven-story building overlooking embassies and U.S. military bases.
From the building, insurgents fired rockets that exploded in the areas of the British, German and Canadian embassies. They kept Afghan officials at bay for hours by wounding the occasional police officer with well-placed sniper shots. The insurgents used the same tactic in September, when they fired rockets at the U.S. Embassy and central Kabul from an unfinished building.
Strawberry and apple carts were abandoned in the streets below the high-rise. Shattered cars and a sport-utility vehicle with its doors flung open sat on the road.
U.K. Foreign Secretary William Hague said all British Embassy staffers were safe, and he praised the Afghan response to the attacks, saying they illustrated "the significant progress that has been made in ensuring that Afghans can look after their own security."
On the other side of town, insurgents stormed another construction site and started firing on the Afghan Parliament compound and nearby Russian Embassy.
At least two lawmakers, including the deputy speaker of the lower house, grabbed machine guns and climbed to the roof as they tried to repel the attack.
"If they are attacking the house of the nation, I have to fight them," said Lalai Hamidzai, one of the two lawmakers who fought off the attack. "We are representatives of the nation. It is the obligation of every Afghan to fight the war against terror."
As the attack began in the early afternoon, one witness reported seeing six individuals enter a building under construction across from a military base on the outskirts of Kabul, and then start firing into the compound from the building's upper floors. One Afghan army soldier reported seeing smoke rising from the base.
The U.S. Embassy in Kabul said on Sunday that its staff was on lockdown as the attacks unfolded and that all of its personnel were accounted for and unhurt.
In Jalalabad, suicide bombers staged two attacks aimed at the U.S. military: In one, Afghan forces targeted an SUV with four suicide bombers near the military airport, detonating the vehicle before it could cause more-serious damage. A second targeted another base, causing some coalition and Afghan casualties, according to a Western official in Kabul.
In Gardez, local officials said, the U.S.-led military coalition targeted a university building where insurgents were holed up. Coalition helicopters and jets pounded the building and reduced it to rubble, according to local officials.
In Pul-i-Alam, officials said four suicide bombers hit a school and a four more targeted a U.S. military base.
Write to                 Dion Nissenbaum at dion.nissenbaum@wsj.com
Copyright 2012 Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved
This copy is for your personal, non-commercial use only. Distribution and use of this material are governed by our Subscriber Agreement and by copyright law. For non-personal use or to order multiple copies, please contact Dow Jones Reprints at 1-800-843-0008 or visit
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Armed insurgents staged a series of attacks in Kabul and across Afghanistan, launching their annual spring offensive with their largest assault on the capital since the Taliban were ousted from power more than a decade ago.
U.S. officials said a free-trade agreement with Colombia will go into effect on May 15, boosting the prospect of U.S. exports to the Andean nation.
Negotiations between Iran and international powers over Tehran's nuclear program are facing fire from Israel and American lawmakers, who fear Iran is trying to forestall additional economic sanctions while continuing to advance its nuclear work.
Ten presidential candidates were preparing to appeal their exclusion from  elections scheduled for next month.
Two leading opposition activists in Belarus were pardoned and freed from prison after 16 months of escalating Western pressure on President Alexander Lukashenko to end a broad crackdown on dissent.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Negotiations between Iran and international powers over Tehran's nuclear program are facing fire from Israel and American lawmakers, who fear Iran is trying to forestall additional economic sanctions while continuing to advance its nuclear work.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Armed insurgents staged a series of attacks in Kabul and across Afghanistan, launching their annual spring offensive with their largest assault on the capital since the Taliban were ousted from power more than a decade ago.
Ten presidential candidates were preparing to appeal their exclusion from  elections scheduled for next month.
U.S. officials said a free-trade agreement with Colombia will go into effect on May 15, boosting the prospect of U.S. exports to the Andean nation.
The North Korean dictator spoke publicly for the first time, declaring before a giant crowd gathered to commemorate his late grandfather's 100th birthday that the country will continue putting military matters above the economy.
Armed insurgents staged a series of attacks in Kabul and across Afghanistan, launching their annual spring offensive with their largest assault on the capital since the Taliban were ousted from power more than a decade ago.
U.S. officials said a free-trade agreement with Colombia will go into effect on May 15, boosting the prospect of U.S. exports to the Andean nation.
Ten presidential candidates were preparing to appeal their exclusion from  elections scheduled for next month.
Save This &amp;darr; More
The attacks on foreign embassies, Parliament and military bases in Kabul unfolded in rapid succession, halting normal life in the city. Gunfire and explosions, which emptied the streets during a normally busy workday, continued into the night.
The coordinated violence in Kabul and the eastern cities of Gardez, Jalalabad and Pul-i-Alam, marked the first significant salvo from the Taliban insurgency this ...
Do we need religion to have ethics? Is it possible that a world without religion can be, on the whole, a better place to live?
Do you think the U.S. economy is improving?
Should individual income tax withholding be abolished?
Outsourcing: How far does it go?
If one is not religious and does not believe in an afterlife, then what is the purpose of life?
The latest news and analysis delivered to your in-box. Check the boxes below to sign up.
The email address null is already associated with another account. Please enter a different email address:
Thank you !You will receive  in your inbox.
The latest news and analysis delivered to your in-box. Check the boxes below to sign up.
The email address null is already associated with another account. Please enter a different email address:
Thank you !You will receive  in your inbox.
Your question to the Journal Community Your comments on articles will show your real name  and not a username.Why?
Why use your real name? The Journal Community encourages thoughtful dialogue and meaningful connections between real people. We require the use of your full name to authenticate your identity. The quality of conversations can deteriorate when real identities are not provided.
Create a Journal Community profile to avoid this message in the future. (As a member you agree to use your real name when participating in the Journal Community)
Your participation access with Journal Community has been disabled due to violation of Journal Community Guidelines.
If you feel you have reached this status change in error, please contact TBD@wsj.com
</text>
</article>