<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>7905</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/naharnet-en-d35b5be3469d0c3223631b3f84ccdcf0.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g491</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/11/2012 10:03:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>• Kofi Annan hopes for 'improved conditions' within 24 hours• Syrian government has promised ceasefire - Annan• Fresh violence reported including shelling in Homs
9.45am: Syria: The government news agency, Sana, issued a lengthy report this morning of the press conference given by the Russian and Syrian foreign ministers following their meeting yesterday in Moscow.
The report begins with the Syrian minister, Walid al-Moallem, saying "that the Syrian government has withdrawn army units from some provinces, yet terrorism activities escalated and spread to other areas". This suggests the regime will resist calls for a full-scale withdrawal as required by the Annan plan and demand that opposition fighters be disarmed first.
Moallem also denied reports that he had asked Annan for "written guarantees from armed groups and countries sponsoring them":
"I asked Annan to contact the armed groups and the countries supporting them ... I asked him to send me a letter on the results of these communications," he said, affirming that the Syrian government is prepared for national dialogue when all the opposition is ready for it, adding that Syria welcomes Russia's offer to host a conference to prepare for national dialogue.
An obstacle further down the line, if the Annan plan eventually gets as far as sending UN observers to monitor a ceasefire in Syria, is that Syria seems to be claiming a right vet the observers. Moallem said observers will be accepted "as long as Syria has a say in the choice of countries from which the observers come and that they respect Syria's sovereignty".
The agency's report also refers to the tensions with Turkey:
Moallem said that Syria is a sovereign country and that it has the right to defend this sovereignty against any violation, adding that unfortunately Turkey is part of the crisis in Syria and it should announce its commitment to Annan's plan on the basis of the respect of all states to the Syrian sovereignty.
He pointed out that Turkey doesn't just host those who were forced to flee their homes by terrorists, but it also hosts armed groups and establishes camps for them and allows these groups to smuggle weapons into Syria and to infiltrate the Syrian borders in violation of Annan's mission which calls for halting the use of violence by all sides.
In an interesting side note, Russian foreign minister Sergei Lavrov referred to the large Russian community in Syria – a factor that is not often mentioned:
Lavrov noted that there are more than 100,000 Russians living in Syria, and that the Russian Embassy in Syria sends information that show that the opposition in Syria isn't entirely peaceful, explaining that Russia received information about the discovery of landmines, explosives and weapons and many terrorist activities that affected several cities and the shelling of Syrian armed forces by the opposition.
9.20am: This video purports to show shelling in Khalidya, in Homs, this morning.
The Local Co-ordination Committees activist group says there has also been shelling in the Homs neighbourhoods of Qarabees and Jourah al-Shiah.Qarabees looks devastated in this video uploaded yesterday.
9.09am: Annan's optimism is not shared by the US ambassador to the UN, Susan Rice, as she made plain on Twitter last night.
— Susan Rice (@AmbassadorRice) April 10, 2012
— Susan Rice (@AmbassadorRice) April 10, 2012
8.51am: Good morning. Welcome to Middle East Live. The UN and Arab League envoy, Kofi Annan, remains optimistic that a ceasefire will take effect in Syria by tomorrow morning but not many seem to share that view. Meanwhile, activists report continuing attacks.
• Annan said the Syrian government have assured him they will respect a ceasefire with rebel forces, less than 24 hours before a deadline to suspend hostilities. "I have received government assurances they will respect the ceasefire. If everyone respects it I think by 6 in the morning on Thursday we shall see improved conditions on the ground," he  said during a visit to Tehran to shore up support for his six-point peace plan.
• Activists are reporting fresh violence, despite the impending deadline.  The Local Coordination Committees activist group says there is shelling of several rebel-held neighborhoods in the central city of Homs. It also reports tanks firing in the southern town of Deraa and military aircraft flying over Lattakia and Duamair, in Damascus suburbs. The British-based Syrian Observatory for Human Rights says "tens of army vehicles" are deploying in the southern town of Maaraba, in Deraa, amid intense shooting.
• Western governments have expressed scepticism about the prospects for a ceasefire after heavy casualties were reported on Tuesday. France called it a "flagrant and unacceptable lie" for Syria to claim it had already withdrawn its forces from populated areas, as required. Both Britain and the US said there was "no evidence" the Syrian government was adhering to Annan's peace plan.
• The Local Co-ordination Committees activist group claimed 101 people were killed on Tuesday, when government forces were supposed to begin pulling back from populated areas. The death toll, which cannot be independently verified, included a mass grave that the LCC said was found containing 37 bodies in Deir Balba, in Homs. Activists in Homs told the Guardian shelling is continuing and they are running low on food and hope.
• The UK government is offering a promininent Libyan dissident more than £1m in compensation for being brutally treated by Muammar Gaddafi's secret police. The government has offered the money to Abdel Hakim Belhaj in a move that would avoid MI6 appearing in open court, where it would face the prospect of explaining its role and that of ministers, the Guardian has been told.
• Formula One supremo Bernie Ecclestone has said teams can decide whether or not to compete at next week's Bahrain Grand Prix but if they choose not to go they will be in breach of agreement. That raises the prospect of any team that pulls out facing a bill of millions of pounds.
• Danish Prime Minister Helle Thorning-Schmidt, who holds the rotating EU presidency said that the condition of imprisoned Bahraini-Danish Danish activist Abdulhadi al-Khawaja is "very critical". The Danish ambassador to Bahrain was allowed a short, 20-minute visit with Khawaja at his military hospital bed on Tuesday. The spokesperson for EU foreign policy chief Catherine Asthon urged "the Bahraini authorities to take all appropriate measures to find a humanitarian solution to Mr Khawaja's deteriorating health situation, as a matter of absolute urgency".
More from Middle East Live on
More 			minute by minutes
Syria crisis - UN peacekeeping team heading for Damascus - live updates
Syria crisis - Wednesday 28 March
Valerie Amos and Kofi Annan to visit Syria - Monday 5 March 2012
Syria, Libya and Middle East unrest - Thursday 7 July 2011
5 comments, displaying  first
Show comments in new window
11 April 2012 9:13AM
The UN is so ridiculously weak-willed and toothless it's beyond a joke. The only time they ever act is when it's too late.
11 April 2012 9:22AM
How long is the ceasefire meant to last?
11 April 2012 9:31AM
Recent tensions in Libya means that there have been record numbers of refugees crossing the border into Tunisia over the last few days with over 10,000 crossing in one day alone
This displacement of families is the untold story behind the recent military interventions in Middle Eastern countries and life has changed drastically for these people for the worse. Peace must be given every chance. The Syrian government have assured Annan they will respect a ceasefire with the rebels due to start tomorrow. The rebels have given no such assurances but pressure must be put on BOTH sides to respect the ceasefire....
11 April 2012 9:36AM
10k refugees in one day to Tunisia - quite a figure.  What's your source of information?
11 April 2012 9:56AM
Response to TrueBrit1066, 11 April 2012 9:31AM
10k refugees in one day to Tunisia - quite a figure. What's your source of information?
The source is Tunisia Live  which was Tunisia's first news website and as far as I am aware is quite respected. Here's the link
Between 10,000 and 12,000 Libyans enter Tunisia from Libya in 24 Hours
Follow events live with our correspondents and a network of selected Twitter users
syrianews: The day Hafez al-Assad died http://t.co/CQ5HsYDF
Iraqis celebrated the Arab Spring that changed the regimes of Tunisia, Egypt and Yemen.
I was traveling last week so I didn't get around to posting this when it came out, but I recently wrote an article about Iraqi universities and the challenges they face for The Chronicle of Higher...
On the evening of 29 March, a line in my twitter feed read, “You don’t want to mess with Iran’s lady ninjas.” Cara Park’s snarky comment had been retweeted by someone I follow in Cairo. I clicked her...
Eastern Libya declares autonomy. In spite of international headlines such as this one, talk of the country’s impending disintegration is misleading.
Latest from the blogs
Zeitgeist is an experiment in showing trending news, topics and articles from the Guardian. Find out more in our blog post.
Search the Guardian bookshop
</text>
</article>