<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>12597</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/AP-71ac26b2886e2788491329ae88af5710.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g147</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/19/2012 10:38:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>BAGHDAD, April 19 (Xinhua) -- Up to 18 people were killed and 72 wounded in a series of bomb attacks in and near Baghdad on Thursday morning, an Interior Ministry source said.
The deadliest attack occurred in Baghdad northern neighborhood of Kadhmiyah when a car bomb went off near a hotel and killed up to three people and wounded 20 others, the source said on condition of anonymity.
In central Baghdad, another car bomb detonated near a convoy of vehicles belonging to the Iraqi Health Ministry in al-Talaie Square, killing two of the minister's bodyguards and wounding four people, the source said.
It was not clear yet whether the minister was at the scene when the attack occurred, the source added.
In a separate incident, a roadside bomb went off near a crowd of construction workers in al-Amil neighborhood, killing up to two workers and wounding 17 others, he said.
In western Baghdad, two gunmen were killed in Ghazaliyah district when a roadside bomb detonated while they were trying to emplace it in the district, according to the source.
Also in the capital, two people were killed and six wounded when a booby-trapped car exploded in Palestine Street in eastern Baghdad, the source said.
In southeastern Baghdad, a roadside bomb ripped through Zaafaraniyah district, wounding five civilians, the source added.
Near Baghdad, a suicide bomber blew up his car bomb near a military checkpoint in the town of Tarmiyah, some 30 km north of Baghdad, killing a soldier and wounding six others, the source said.
Separately, a suicide bomber blew up his explosive vest in the industrial district in Taji area, some 20 km north of Baghdad, killing five people and wounding nine others, the source added.
Also in Taji area, two roadside bombs detonated in the area, killing a civilian and wounding five others, he said.
Earlier, the police reported the killing of 10 people and the wounding of five others in separate bomb attacks in the morning in Iraq's province of Salahudin.
Violence is still common in the Iraqi cities despite the dramatic decrease since its peak in 2006 and 2007 when the country was engulfed in sectarian killings.
Special Report: Situation in Iraq
</text>
</article>