<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>10830</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/dailystar-LB-748b96eae994d96e112498b7c9645a91.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g169</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/16/2012 9:58:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>DAMASCUS, Syria, April 16 (UPI) -- Syrian forces raided the city of Hama Monday after shelling the rebel city of Homs and attacking other towns before U.N. truce monitors started their mission.
The raid of Hama's Karm Horani neighborhood amid a "random-detention campaign," along with sniper fire that killed at least two civilians, coincided with "intense and indiscriminate gunfire" Monday by regime forces stationed at military checkpoints in the Damascus suburbs, the opposition Local Coordination Committees of Syria said in a Web posting monitored by United Press International.
The attacks, on the fifth day of a shaky cease-fire, escalated fighting that raged Sunday, with tank shells, mortar rounds and other explosive projectiles pummeling key opposition hotbeds, including war-ravaged Homs, recently under siege by the Syrian army; Idlib, previously targeted for hosting the opposition Free Syrian Army; and Daraa, where fighting was exacerbated by water-supply cutoffs by Syrian forces, opposition groups said.
"The army is shelling with mortars and tanks, and small rockets," Homs activist Waleed al-Fares told the British newspaper The Daily Telegraph by Skype. "Today we have 10 killed and 15 wounded. They broke the truce. They are doing this because there are no observers yet."
Fares said the Homs attack was a warning to residents not to talk to the U.N. truce monitors when they arrive -- in line with similar allegations made ahead of the arrival of Arab League observers in December 2011.
"They are attacking this area because there are too many activists there," Fares told the newspaper. "They are teaching people a lesson, not to go and talk when the observers arrive."
Syria said through state television its actions were defensive maneuvers against "armed terrorist groups" that broke the truce.
The differing reports and allegations could not be independently confirmed because the government has severely restricted media coverage of the conflict.
An advance team of six unarmed U.N. truce monitors -- approved unanimously Saturday by the 15-member Security Council, including Russia and China -- were to begin work Monday after flying to Damascus Sunday night.
Some two dozen other monitors were to join them in the coming days, U.N. officials said.
A larger monitoring team, expected to number about 250, is to be dispatched only if the cease-fire is deemed to be holding, the officials said.
The cease-fire, which began Thursday, is part of a broader peace plan brokered by U.N.-Arab League envoy Kofi Annan last month as part of international efforts to stop 13 months of violence.
The opposition demands the resignation of President Bashar Assad and an end to nearly five decades of Baath Party rule.
</text>
</article>