<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>14739</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/trust-eecd6f41b4d1a15744c6191ab1b3dd29.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g985</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/4/2012 2:27:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Explore news, videos, and much more based on what your friends are reading and watching. Publish your own activity and retain full control.
Pakistani security officials examine &amp;hellip;
Map showing Bajaur district in &amp;hellip;
Pakistani security officials examine &amp;hellip;
Pakistani relatives push a stretcher &amp;hellip;
A teenage suicide bomber targeted police in a bustling Pakistan town square on Friday, killing at least 20 people and wounding dozens in the tribal area near the Afghan border, officials said.
The Taliban claimed responsibility for the attack, saying it targeted the local chief and deputy of a tribal police force who were recruited by the government to help defeat an Islamist insurgency in the northwest.
Only a day earlier, documents released by the United States showed that Osama bin Laden had been unhappy with the Pakistani Taliban for killing civilians and that Al-Qaeda leaders wrote to its chief, Hakimullah Mehsud, urging him to mend his ways.
The bomber, who intelligence officials said was aged 14 to 16, detonated explosives strapped to his chest in Khar, the main town of Bajaur district. Bajaur has been one of the toughest battlegrounds in Pakistan's fight against a northwestern Taliban insurgency.
It was the deadliest bombing in Pakistan since March 2, when at least 22 people were killed by a suicide attack on a mosque in the tribal district of Khyber.
"Twenty people, including five policemen, were killed and 46 others were wounded. Some shops and a restaurant were destroyed," Islam Zeb, the administrative head of Bajaur tribal district, told AFP.
The local tribal police chief and his deputy were among the dead.
It was the third bomb attack in two days in Bajaur, after twin blasts killed five people -- including pro-government elders and security personnel -- on Thursday.
The violence highlights the insurgency in Pakistan at a time when Islamabad is under renewed US pressure crack down on militants based on its soil, such as the Haqqani network, blamed for a spectacular assault on Kabul last month.
The military conducted major anti-Taliban offensives in Bajaur in August 2008 and February 2009, and has repeatedly declared the district secure.
But militants have still proved able to strike.
Ehsanullah Ehsan, spokesman for the Pakistani Taliban claimed responsibility for Friday's attack, saying that anyone involved in "activity" against the Taliban "will be treated with iron hands".
"Our attacks will continue until (US) drone strikes end," Ehsan told AFP.
According to an AFP tally, around 5,000 people have been killed in attacks blamed on the Taliban and its allies since July 2007, when Pakistani troops raided an extremist mosque in Islamabad, sparking a bloody insurgency.
Pakistan has lost more than 3,000 soldiers in the fight against homegrown insurgents but has resisted US pressure to do more to eliminate havens used by those fighting the Americans in Afghanistan.
The United States conducts a secretive drone war against Taliban and Al-Qaeda militants on Pakistani soil, despite increasingly vocal public denunciations from the government, which initially gave its tacit approval to the strikes.
Relations between Pakistan and the United States have lapsed into stalemate since the covert American raid that killed bin Laden last May and US air strikes that inadvertently killed 24 Pakistani soldiers in November.
Pakistan has shut down NATO supply lines into Afghanistan and last month parliament approved new guidelines on relations with the United States, which included a call for an end to drone strikes.
It remains unclear whether the impasse with Washington can be solved before this month's NATO summit on Afghanistan in Chicago, to which Islamabad has been invited.
Bin Laden family deported from Paki &amp;hellip;
Medics attend to a man who was injured &amp;hellip;
US drone 'kills three militants' in &amp;hellip;
Taliban hit Kabul on Osama bin Laden &amp;hellip;
Best Buy employee wrongly 'outs' man
Pets wreak havoc in hockey player's digs
Demi Moore cuts another tie to Kutcher
Breakthrough in Chinese activist's case
BEIJING (Reuters) - China said on Friday blind dissident Chen Guangcheng could apply to study abroad, a move praised by U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton and suggesting an end may be near to a diplomatic &amp;hellip; More »Clinton applauds China allowing dissident to apply to study in U.S.
BEIJING (Reuters) - China said on Friday blind dissident Chen Guangcheng could apply to study abroad, a move praised by U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton and suggesting an end may be near to a diplomatic crisis between Beijing and Washington. But rights activists sounded a note of caution over expectations of a quick &amp;hellip;
BEIJING (Reuters) - Secretary of State Hillary Clinton said on Friday that the United States was willing to work with North Korea if it changed its ways, and also said more pressure should be brought to &amp;hellip; More »Clinton says U.S. willing to work with North Korea if it reforms
BEIJING (Reuters) - Secretary of State Hillary Clinton said on Friday that the United States was willing to work with North Korea if it changed its ways, and also said more pressure should be brought to bear on Sudan and Syria. Speaking in Beijing at the end of two-days of high-level meetings overshadowed by a crisis over &amp;hellip;
KHARTOUM (Reuters) - South Sudan accused Sudan on Friday of attacking its military positions in an oil region, imperiling the chances of a promised ceasefire between the neighbours, but Khartoum denied &amp;hellip; More »S. Sudan accuses Sudan of bombing in blow to talks
KHARTOUM (Reuters) - South Sudan accused Sudan on Friday of attacking its military positions in an oil region, imperiling the chances of a promised ceasefire between the neighbours, but Khartoum denied the charge. The 1,800 km-long (1,200 mile) border between the two countries had been largely quiet for the past 48 hours, &amp;hellip;
MOSCOW (Reuters) - When Vladimir Putin stood for re-election to the presidency in 2004, he named a new government even before the vote. Now, days before he is sworn in as Kremlin chief for a third time, &amp;hellip; More »Analysis: The ins and outs of Russia's next government
MOSCOW (Reuters) - When Vladimir Putin stood for re-election to the presidency in 2004, he named a new government even before the vote. Now, days before he is sworn in as Kremlin chief for a third time, the shape of his next administration remains a mystery. Although outgoing President Dmitry Medvedev has been nominated &amp;hellip;
MIAMI (Reuters) - Disgraced former press baron Conrad Black was released from a Florida prison on Friday after ending his sentence but he was immediately taken into custody by U.S. immigration officials. &amp;hellip; More »Former press baron Conrad Black released from U.S. prison
MIAMI (Reuters) - Disgraced former press baron Conrad Black was released from a Florida prison on Friday after ending his sentence but he was immediately taken into custody by U.S. immigration officials. "He is in ICE custody," said Nestor Yglesias, a spokesman for U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement. Yglesias declined &amp;hellip;
Get breaking news, videos, blogs and more at ABC News. More »Breaking News from ABC News
View the latest slideshow galleries on Yahoo! News. More »Photos of the day
These flexible online degrees could help you go to school on your terms.
Thinking about going back to school? Find out which online degrees rank highest in popularity.
</text>
</article>