<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>10250</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/dailytimesPK-50e55a57c0ea31517d13136a8afe456d.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g925</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/15/2012 7:41:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Dow Jones Reprints: This copy is for your personal, non-commercial use only. To order presentation-ready copies for distribution to your colleagues, clients or customers, use the Order Reprints tool at the bottom of any article or visit
"Let us move forward to the final victory," Mr. Kim said as he finished the speech with the term associated with his grandfather Kim Il Sung's oft-stated desire to control South Korea as well as the North.
North Korea's leader Kim Jong Eun waves at the end of a major military parade to mark 100 years since the birth of the country's founder and his grandfather, Kim Il Sung, in Pyongyang on Sunday.
Mr. Kim's only reference to the country's pursuit of weapons of mass destruction came when he said the time when North Korea could be threatened by the nuclear weapons of other countries was "forever over." He didn't mention Friday's failed launch of what North Korea called a rocket and other countries feared was a long-range missile in disguise, which broke apart less than two minutes after launch.
Even so, the speech stuck close to the hard-line orthodoxy of the Kim family regime, which has controlled North Korea since its founding in 1948, that is built around extreme race-based nationalism, Confucian hierarchy and a nominal embrace of socialism.
While he said North Koreans should "tighten their belts" no longer, he also said military strength should be the country's "first, second and third" priority. And he said peace was important, but "the country's pride is more important."
Mr. Kim's approximately 20-minute speech was the highlight of a two-hour ceremony at Kim Il Sung Square, the central plaza in the North Korean capital Pyongyang.
Tens of thousands of people in the square participated in the event by holding up placards to form tableaus of the words "Kim Il Sung" and "Military First." Thousands of goose-stepping soldiers, and dozens of military vehicles, including tanks and mobile rocket launchers, then paraded by.
Mr. Kim began his speech by describing his "purest respect and greatest honor to comrades Kim Il Sung and Kim Jong Il," his grandfather and father. Kim Jong Eun took control of the country after the death of his father in December.
With the speech, Mr. Kim took his latest step to create a public image that is more like his grandfather, who could be gregarious in public settings, than his father, who was more reserved and whose voice was broadcast only once. In his public appearances, Mr. Kim has often been seen hugging and walking arm-in-arm with people.
Mr. Kim, who is believed to be 28 or 29 years old, appeared at ease in front of the massive crowd at Kim Il Sung Square, smiling and waving and shaking clasped hands above his head. The event was broadcast live on North Korean state TV.
He wore a dark Mao-like suit for Sunday's event, though the nation's main newspaper last week published a photo of Mr. Kim in a western suit and tie to commemorate the news that the Ruling Workers' Party had bestowed him with the top-ranking title of First Secretary.
North Korea, which last week permitted about 50 foreign reporters in to see preparations for the rocket launch, on Friday and Saturday allowed another sizable group of foreign reporters to witness Sunday's event.
For several years, North Korea's regime has built up the 100th anniversary of Kim Il Sung's birth as a turning point in its drive to become a "strong and prosperous nation." Over the past year, hundreds of construction projects around the country have been under way, often using people diverted from other work or education, and timed to be finished on or around the anniversary date.
A month ago, North Korea announced it would also launch a rocket into space during the celebration period, drawing international condemnation for violating United Nations Security Council prohibitions on its testing of missile technology. The criticism continued despite the rocket's failure on Friday.
Copyright 2012 Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved
This copy is for your personal, non-commercial use only. Distribution and use of this material are governed by our Subscriber Agreement and by copyright law. For non-personal use or to order multiple copies, please contact Dow Jones Reprints at 1-800-843-0008 or visit
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
President Barack Obama replied Saturday to calls from Latin America to consider legalizing drugs, saying it is legitimate to debate the matter, but that he remains opposed.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Fresh signs of stress among Spanish banks sent shudders through European markets on Friday and helped push U.S. stocks to their worst week this year.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
The Secret Service put 11 agents on administrative leave amid allegations they brought prostitutes back to their hotel rooms while preparing for a visit by President Barack Obama.
The announcement followed more than 10 hours of talks between Tehran and five permanent members of the United Nations Security Council, plus Germany.
British consular officials in China expressed suspicions in November over the death of British businessman Neil Heywood, but the matter initially wasn't pursued further.
Egypt's Presidential Elections Commission will exclude 10 candidates, including three prominent frontrunners, from presidential elections.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Do we need religion to have ethics? Is it possible that a world without religion can be, on the whole, a better place to live?
Do you think the U.S. economy is improving?
Should individual income tax withholding be abolished?
If one is not religious and does not believe in an afterlife, then what is the purpose of life?
Do you ride for transportation or for fitness, or both? Tell us what your training ride consists of, or your morning bike commute? What kind of bike do you ride, and what's your typical weekend ride?
The latest news and analysis delivered to your in-box. Check the boxes below to sign up.
The email address null is already associated with another account. Please enter a different email address:
Thank you !You will receive  in your inbox.
The latest news and analysis delivered to your in-box. Check the boxes below to sign up.
The email address null is already associated with another account. Please enter a different email address:
Thank you !You will receive  in your inbox.
Subscriber Content Read Preview
Your question to the Journal Community Your comments on articles will show your real name  and not a username.Why?
Why use your real name? The Journal Community encourages thoughtful dialogue and meaningful connections between real people. We require the use of your full name to authenticate your identity. The quality of conversations can deteriorate when real identities are not provided.
Create a Journal Community profile to avoid this message in the future. (As a member you agree to use your real name when participating in the Journal Community)
Your participation access with Journal Community has been disabled due to violation of Journal Community Guidelines.
If you feel you have reached this status change in error, please contact TBD@wsj.com
</text>
</article>