<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>1564</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/news-yahoo-fe8138b9f1da91b515ba71c6d3a6c137.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1029</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>12/6/2011 11:34:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>An Afghan police officer stands guard at the scene of a suicide attack in Kabul. Picture: AP  
&lt;!-- google_ad_section_start(name=story_introduction, weight=high) --&gt;
A massive blast at the entrance to a shrine in central Kabul  where Shi'ite Muslims had gathered today to mark Ashura left  at least 30 people dead including children, an AFP photographer  said.
"A suicide bomber detonated his explosives in the Abu-Ul Fazil  shrine," Kabul police said in a statement.
A security official speaking on condition of anonymity told AFP  that it was believed the bomber arrived with a group of Shi'ite  pilgrims from Logar province, south of Kabul.
Separately, four people were killed in Mazar-i-Sharif when  another blast struck a shrine in the northern city. It was not  immediately clear whether Shi'ites were targeted in that attack.
"It was an explosion not a suicide bombing. It was some  explosives hidden in a bicycle," said Lal Mohammad Ahmadzai, a  police spokesman for northern Afghanistan, adding that four other  people had also been injured.
Shi'ites were banned from marking Ashura in public under the  Taliban who ruled Afghanistan until 2001. This year, there are more  Ashura monuments around the city than usual including black shrines  and flags.
There was no immediate claim of responsibility for either of the  blasts from the Taliban or other insurgent groups operating in  Afghanistan.
The attacks came shortly after a major conference on  Afghanistan's future, held in the German city of Bonn, 10 years  after talks there which put in place an interim government after  US-led troops ousted the Taliban.
However, Pakistan and the Taliban - both seen as pivotal to any  end to the bloody strife in Afghanistan - decided to stay away from  the talks, undermining already modest hopes for real progress.
The 10-day Ashura ceremonies, which began on November 27 but  peak on Tuesday, mark the slaughter of Imam Hussein, the grandson  of the Prophet Mohammed, near Karbala by armies of the caliph Yazid  in 680AD.
Tradition holds that the revered imam was decapitated and his  body mutilated. His death was a formative event in Shi'ite Islam.
Sectarian violence periodically flares between Shi'ites, who  beat and whip themselves in religious fervour during Ashura, and  Sunnis, who oppose the public display of grief.
Yesterday, at least 28 people were killed and 78 wounded in a  wave of bomb attacks in central Iraq against Shi'ite pilgrims  making their way to Karbala.
TEEN spends first his hours at home from Bali taunting the media, then calls the cops to "drag them away".
128 comments on this story
Meet the 20 amateur photographer who've blown the judges away to make it to the finalists of this year's Grab Photographic Competition
They're always a bundle of joy - but for some, a bigger bundle than expected!
Daily Telegraph photographer Phil Hillyard has been named the Nikon Walkley Press Photographer of the Year
PRIME Minister Julia Gillard has made a surprise visit to Afghanistan, where she visited Aussie troops and met with president Hamid Karzai.
Demonstrators clash with riot police in a violent protest in Tahrir Square, Cairo.
A fire has broken out in a Quakers Hill nursing home
UPDATE: Community struggling to deal with tragedy as tributes pour in for "happy innocent girls".
ENTIRE Eurozone placed on credit downgrade watch. That's not good news if you want banks to pass on a rate cut.
THE Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) has cut the cash rate to 4.25 per cent from 4.5 per cent at its December board meeting.
LIZ Hurley will celebrate the festive season in Australia and reveals why she'll be getting hot in the kitchen.
TRAVELLERS will be able to easily identify quality tourism products in Australia with a new Heart Foundation-style tick of approval on TripAdvisor.
SONY turn a lounge room into a scene from Tron in viral video - without the need for digital editing. Find out how they did it.
Copyright 2011 News Limited. All times AEDT (GMT +11).
</text>
</article>