<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>24895</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/jrep-4e2586973c0e76af32b4f04828c417da.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g462</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/21/2012 11:07:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>      May 21, 2012 18:27:53
A suicide bomber dressed in military uniform has blown himself up in the middle of a battalion of soldiers in the Yemeni capital Sanaa, killing at least 50 people and wounding dozens of others.
"There are at least 50 dead and the toll could rise," a military official said, speaking on condition of anonymity.
The bomber detonated his explosives in the middle of a battalion rehearsing for an army parade to mark the 22nd anniversary of the unification of north and south Yemen, the official added.
Witnesses said human remains were scattered across the site of the blast at Sanaa's Sabeen Square, where the Yemeni government often holds large military parades.
If the death toll is correct, the attack is the most deadly since president Abdrabuh Mansur Hadi took power in February with a pledge to fight Al Qaeda's growing presence in the county.
It comes 10 days into a massive army offensive against Al Qaeda in Yemen's restive southern Abyan province, where the jihadists have seized control of a string of towns and cities in attacks launched since last May.
Other reports, however, put the death toll as low as 20.
If you have inside knowledge of a topic in the news, contact the ABC News Online Investigative Unit.
View images from the career of Bee Gees singer Robin Gibb.
View a chronology of key events in the Lockerbie bombing case.
See photos of a rare solar eclipse which is unfolding across North America and Asia this morning.
The English town made famous by spoof rapper Ali G has changed its name.
This service may include material from Agence France-Presse (AFP), APTN, Reuters, AAP, CNN and the BBC World Service which is copyright and cannot be reproduced.
AEST = Australian Eastern Standard Time which is 10 hours ahead of UTC (Greenwich Mean Time)
</text>
</article>