<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>16650</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/dailystar-LB-adc1ab5a728a058fb0f725bfcf39fe8a.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g964</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/12/2012 12:07:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>May. 12, 2012 - 06:13AM JST
Tens of thousands of protesters defied Syrian regime gunfire and took to the streets Friday, as state TV said the army foiled a would-be suicide attack a day after twin bombings in Damascus killed dozens.
At least 12 people died across Syria, including a guard gunned down after a large explosion outside Baath party offices in Aleppo on Friday evening, hours after the suicide bombing was reportedly thwarted in the northern city.
The activist, Mohammed al-Halabi, added however that there was a chance the explosion was caused by a sound bomb.
It came only hours after forces loyal to President Bashar al-Assad opened fire on protesters during a demonstration Aleppo, killing one civilian, said the Observatory.
Also on Friday, state television said the army foiled a would-be suicide attack in Aleppo by a bomber whose car was laden with 1,200 kilos (2,640 pounds) of explosives.
Traditionally a bastion of the Baath party, anti-regime sentiment has been on the rise in the commercial hub of Aleppo in recent months.
Elsewhere, civilians were killed in areas including central Hama and southern Daraa, where an 11-year-old child died from sniper fire, said the Observatory.
Troops shot and wounded five protesters in the capital and 20 in the central town of Helfaya, where two civilians also died, while another demonstrator was killed in Aleppo, it said.
Halabi said the Aleppo protester died from his wounds after regime forces opened fire in Salaheddine neighborhood.
All but one of those killed on Friday were civilians, with one soldier killed and six others wounded in Jisr al-Shugur city in Idlib province when a blast hit their vehicle.
The violence came one day after two huge suicide blasts hit security premises in southern Damascus, causing devastation on an adjacent highway during rush-hour traffic.
At least 55 people died and 372 were hurt in the attacks, the deadliest since the start of the revolt in March 2011.
The attacks have raised fears that extremist elements could be taking advantage of the deadlock in Syria to stoke the unrest.
An Islamist group calling itself Al-Nusra Front claimed responsibility on the Internet for an earlier double bomb attack in Damascus, the SITE Monitoring Service said on Thursday.
It said two bombs it had placed near a military headquarters on a central highway in the capital on May 5 killed around 20 guards.
EU foreign policy chief Catherine Ashton also condemned attacks in the southern town of Deraa and in Damascus.
More than 12,000 people, the majority of them civilians, have died since the uprising began, according to the Observatory, including more than 900 killed since the April 12 truce went into effect.
</text>
</article>