<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>18351</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/trendnews-az-3f400510d92e659249a2d11526c97db1.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g261</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/15/2012 1:27:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>11:55AM BST 15 May 2012
Tehran has accused Israel and the United States of assassinating four Iranian 
  scientists since 2010 in order to sabotage its nuclear programme which the 
  West suspects is hiding Iran's attempt to develop a nuclear weapons 
While Israel has declined to comment on the killings, it regards Iran's 
  nuclear programme as an existential threat and has threatened military 
  action against Tehran. Washington has denied any U.S. role.
Twenty-four year old Majid Jamali Fashi was hanged at Tehran's Evin Prison 
  after being sentenced to death in August last year for the murder of Massoud 
  Ali-Mohammadi, Iran's state news agency quoted the central prosecutor's 
  office as saying. It said he had confessed to the crime.
Ali-Mohammadi was killed in January 2010 when a remote-controlled bomb 
  attached to a motorcycle outside his home in Tehran went off.
The report said Fashi had confessed to travelling to Tel Aviv to receive 
  training from Mossad before returning to Iran to plot the assassination.
Netanyahu prepares for early elections
Israel army chief: other nations could strike Iran
Iran 'undecided' on nuclear arms
Israel warns Hizbollah over Iran
A spokesman for Iran's Atomic Energy Organisation said at the time that 
  Ali-Mohammadi, a 50-year-old Tehran University professor, was not involved 
The most recent attack on an Iranian scientist occurred in January. Mostafa 
  Ahmadi-Roshan - a deputy director of the Natanz uranium enrichment facility 
  - was killed when a magnetic bomb planted on his vehicle detonated.
Israel has a policy of not commenting on the allegations but an unnamed 
  Israeli source previously said the daylight killings provoked panic in 
  surviving colleagues and generate a phenomenon Mossad veterans dub "virtual 
  defection" which hinders Iran's nuclear progress.
Last month, Iranian intelligence officials said they had arrested 15 people 
  they called a "major terror and sabotage network with links to the 
  Zionist regime". The group had plotted to assassinate an Iranian 
  scientist in February, the authorities said.
Iranian officials have also accused Israel of infiltrating neighbouring 
  Azerbaijan to organise attacks against the Islamic Republic.
Unsubstantiated reports in the Iranian media earlier this month said Israel 
  has pushed for the transfer Of 1,200 members of the exiled Iranian rebel 
  group Mujahideen Khalq Organisation (MKO) from their base in Iraq to 
Late last year Israel distanced itself from the MKO's efforts to be removed 
  from the U.S. terrorism blacklist, saying it did not consider the group to 
Iran denies Western accusations it is seeking to develop a nuclear weapons 
  capability, but major powers are pushing Tehran to become more transparent 
  and cooperative ahead of talks later this month.
Israel says it could attack Iran if it thinks that is the only way to stop it 
  from getting nuclear arms.
William Hague, the Foreign Secretary, on Monday warned the European Union 
  would impose tougher sanctions on Iran if it failed to take concrete steps 
  to allay international concerns over its nuclear programme.
Axa Sun Life's Over-50s Plan seems simple, yet for many it's a seriously bad 
  bet, writes Martin Lewis.
Featured Advertising
Search for a property
MORE FROM TELEGRAPH.CO.UK
&amp;copy; Copyright of Telegraph Media Group Limited 2012
Terms and Conditions
</text>
</article>