<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>11064</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/skynews-7d4ae91dfe4a73c8e6577979b85755f1.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g743</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/16/2012 2:16:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Anders Behring Breivik has wept in court as an anti-Islam propaganda video he created was played - but showed no emotion when claiming he killed 77 people in self-defence.
At the start of his trial in Oslo, Breivik made a far-right salute and said he did not recognise the legitimacy of the court, before pleading not guilty - but said he "acknowledges the acts".
According to Sky News, during proceedings Breivik smirked as the prosecution spoke about his early online gaming habits and bomb-making plans - but wept as the court was shown a 12-minute anti-Islam propaganda video he posted online in 2010.
Breivik has admitted killing 77 people by detonating a bomb in the centre of Oslo and opening fire on young people attending a summer camp on Utoya island nearly nine months ago.
The 33-year-old is charged with terrorism, but he believes the attacks were a political act designed to prevent what he described as an Islamic invasion of Norway.
In court, Breivik described himself as a "writer" and told the judges: "I do not recognise the Norwegian courts. You have received your mandate from political parties which support multiculturalism."
Last week, his lawyer told reporters Breivik believes he should be facing a military tribunal, not a criminal court.
The trial began with the prosecution reading out the names and details of those killed and injured in the bombing and shooting spree last July.
Breivik was then asked what his plea would be. He told the court: "I admit to the acts, but not criminal guilt." He will take the stand again on Tuesday.
Svein Holden told the court how Breivik made money by making false diplomas and certificates in his company Diplom Service before 2006, and described his extensive online gaming habits - mostly playing World of Warcraft.
Breivik made Knights Templar uniforms for himself and bought guns and other items connected to weapons, the court heard.
He had rented a farm 90 miles from Oslo, where he wrote his manifesto and started to assemble the bomb from fertilisers, diesel and chemicals.
The 10-week trial, which is being held in a specially-built courtroom that includes sheets of toughened glass behind the defendant, will hear from eyewitnesses, survivors and forensic experts.
His defence lawyer, Vibeke Hein Baera, has told Sky News that part of their strategy is to call a series of extremists as witnesses, to question an initial psychiatric report that deemed Breivik to be criminally insane.
A second report disputed those findings and a panel of two professional and three lay judges will have to decide whether Breivik should be sent for treatment at a psychiatric hospital or jailed.
If Breivik is found sane he faces just 21 years in prison for the killings - though the sentence may be extended indefinitely if he is still considered a threat to society.
If he is found insane, he could spend the rest of his life on the closed psychiatric ward, a fate he has declared would be "worse than death".
He wants to be found sane and accountable for his actions, so that his anti-Islam ideology - presented in the 1,500-page manifesto he published online just before the attacks - will be taken seriously and not considered the ravings of a lunatic.
He is expected to say he wishes he had "gone further", but cameras relaying the trial around the world will be switched off during his evidence to deny him a platform for his extremist views.
Eight people were killed in the devastating explosion and more than 200 were injured.
As survivors stumbled through the rubble, Breivik was already on his way to Utoya island, where the AUF Labour Party was holding its annual summer camp.
After convincing AUF organisers on the mainland that he was a policeman sent to secure the island after the bomb blast in Oslo, he made the short trip over the water. Then the massacre began.
For over an hour he aimed, fired and reloaded as terrified youngsters ran for cover and others fell with fatal gunshot wounds. In all, 186 bullet casings were found on the island.
Tags: News, World, BREIVIK TRAIL, Norway Massacre
Forgotten your Password?
Forgotten your Password?
</text>
</article>