<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>19186</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/voanews-550097e036a0fdc8f3ce1921a95856fb.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g693</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/16/2012 2:56:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Earlier, there was a handover of power with the outgoing president at the Elysee Palace
It is unlikely that Merkel will welcome such a suggestion. She has already affirmed that the pact should not be tampered with, having already been signed by 25 of 27 EU member states and ratified by Greece, Portugal and Slovenia.
Before leaving for Germany, newly elected Hollande chose his Socialist colleague, Jean-Marc Ayrault to be France's new prime minister on Tuesday. Ayrault, who is the long-standing leader of the Socialists in the National Assembly, is widely viewed as a moderate.
The 62-year-old Ayrault is a former German teacher and a Germanophile, which may prove useful when it comes to building a relationship with France's powerful neighbor.
And earlier in the day, at a ceremony at the Elysee Palace in Paris, Hollande was inaugurated as the successor to Nicolas Sarkozy as the French president.
After an official ceremony where Sarkozy handed over the reins to Hollande, Sarkozy and his wife, Carla Bruni, climbed into a car in front of the palace and drove away, officially ending his role as President.
sej/rc (Reuters, dpa, AFP)
French President Hollande has visited Berlin for talks with Chancellor Merkel about Europe's woes. Although eager to show a united front, they struggled to conceal underlying differences in their opinions.
United Nations peace observers have been caught up the latest violence in Syria. One of their cars traveling in a convoy was hit by an improvised explosive device. None of the monitors were injured.
French President Francois Hollande has touched down in Berlin for talks with German Chancellor Angela Merkel. The Socialist president's first trip abroad comes just hours after he was sworn into office.
Ex-tabloid editor Rebekah Brooks has been charged over her alleged role in a phone hacking scandal. The development comes after she was questioned about her links to the British prime minister.
</text>
</article>