<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>8440</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/naharnet-en-d35b5be3469d0c3223631b3f84ccdcf0.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g491</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/11/2012 3:46:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>DAMASCUS, April 10, (Agen-cies): Syrian forces on Tuesday pounded protest hubs in apparent breach of a ceasefire deal brokered by UN-Arab League envoy Kofi Annan, who appealed for his plan to be implemented without preconditions.
Syria said it was abiding by the plan, but Annan accused Damascus of pulling troops from some areas and moving them to others, and the rebel Free Syrian Army warned it would resume attacks if the government offensive does not stop.
Washington said it hoped the UN Security Council would consider action if Annan concludes that Damascus broke its commitments.
The violence drew sharp condemnation from France and Britain, with even Russia urging its ally to act more decisively to implement the truce.
Syrian Foreign Minister Walid Muallem said Damascus begun carrying out the Annan deal by pulling some troops out of certain provinces.
Annan, visiting Syrian refugees in Turkey, said that the Syrian army had indicated it was pulling out of some areas but he had also received reports of troops moving into other parts of the country.
“They have indicated that there has been withdrawals... but we also received indications from other sources that there are movements towards areas which have not been previously targeted,” he told reporters.
“I again appeal to the Syrian government and the Syrian parties to cease violence in accordance (with) the plan,” he told reporters. “I believe there should be no preconditions for stopping violence.”
The Annan plan has been under a cloud since Sunday, when Damascus said it would keep its side of the bargain only if rebels gave guarantees they would also stop fighting, a condition rejected out of hand.
Forces loyal to President Bashar al-Assad also shot four people in the village of Kfar Zeita in the central Hama province, but it was unclear if they were rebels or civilians.
Clashes also rocked the district of Mzeyreeb in the southern province of Daraa, where the dissent movement launched a year ago.
The Local Coordination Committees, one of the main opposition groups inside Syria, said “large military reinforcements” had arrived overnight on the eastern outskirts of Rastan in central Homs province.
The report could not be verified because of curbs on media activity.
Under the Annan deal, Syria was supposed to withdraw its forces from population centres on Tuesday ahead of a complete ceasefire on Thursday.
Activists say Syria has intensified its crackdown since the weekend when around 180 people were killed. On Monday, 105 died in one of the bloodiest days since mid-March last year.
Free Syrian Army spokesman Colonel Kassem Saadeddine warned that rebel forces would resume attacks on regular forces if they do not withdraw.
“If (the regime) does not stop shelling and not withdraw tanks, we will intensify our military operations and launch attacks,” he told AFP.
The head of the opposition Syrian National Council, Burhan Ghalioun, warned that his group, “as the legitimate representative of the people, will not allow the regime to use the (UN) plan as a licence to kill.”
But Muallem insisted Damascus had begun implementing the Annan plan.
“We have already withdrawn military units from different Syrian provinces,” he told a Moscow news conference after talks with Russian counterpart Sergei Lavrov.
Lavrov said Syria should be more decisive in fulfilling the Annan plan, which most notably calls on Syria to pull troops and weaponry out of cities hit by protests.
“We believe their actions could have been more active, more decisive when it comes to the implementation of the plan,” he said.
Lavrov later spoke with Annan by phone, telling him to put more pressure on the rebels to cooperate with his initiative.
He told Annan “the Syrian opposition and states that support it must take urgent measures to ensure a sustainable ceasefire,” and urged him “to step up his work with them along these lines,” the foreign ministry said.
White House spokesman Jay Carney said Washington had so far only seen evidence of further “brutality and aggression” from Assad’s forces.
“We would certainly hope the UN Security Council would evaluate the situation in Syria if in fact Mr Annan finds that the Assad regime has not abided by its own commitments to begin withdrawal by today,” Carney said.
Germany’s UN ambassador, Peter Wittig, said Syria has not complied with the plan and that international measures must be studied.
Assad “has not complied with the Annan plan; instead he has scaled up violence and human rights violations,” Wittig said.
There was equally tough language from London and Paris.
“There is no evidence so far that the Assad regime has any intention of adhering to any agreement it makes,” Britain’s Foreign Secretary William Hague said.
Syrian forces “have ruthlessly subjected whole communities to an inhumane campaign of shelling, forced expulsions and executions.
“All those with influence over the Syrian leadership, including Russia, have a duty to back efforts to stop the violence and to isolate a regime which is as doomed as it is dangerous to the Syrian people,” he added.
French foreign ministry spokesman Bernard Valero called Muallem’s assertion that Syria pulled troops out of some areas “a new expression of a flagrant and unacceptable lie.”
Damascus was also rebuked for violence that spilled over into its neighbours on Monday, killing a Lebanese TV cameraman inside Lebanon and wounding four people in a Turkish camp for Syrian refugees.
Turkish Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan accused Syria of a “clear violation” of common frontiers, while Lebanon demanded an investigation.
The United Nations says more than 9,000 people have been killed since anti-regime protests broke out in March 2011. Monitors put the number at more than 10,000.
Fifty-two people including 28 civilians were killed across Syria on Tuesday, the day the government was expected to pull its forces from protest hubs under a UN-Arab League peace plan, monitors said.
Among the dead were 19 members of the regime’s security forces and five rebels killed in fighting in several provinces, said the Syrian Observatory for Human Rights.
Six civilians were killed in bombardment of the Khaldiyeh district of Homs city in the centre of the country, and a seventh was shot dead in the Bab Tadmur neighbourhood.
In Hama province, also in central Syria, seven civilians were killed in Kfar Zeita, the scene of fierce clashes with rebels and aerial bombardment on Monday, the Britain-based monitoring group said.
Another four civilians were reported killed in Daraa province in the south, and a child was killed at Harasta near the capital, the Observatory said.
In Deir Ezzor, a civilian was killed by gunfire, while eight others were killed in the region of Aleppo. Five rebels were also reported killed in Daraa, Homs, Hama and Aleppo.
In addition, 11 soldiers were killed in the northeast region of Hassakeh, five in Aleppo province and three near the Turkish border.
The latest violence came as government forces were to have withdrawn from protest hubs under the peace plan drawn up by UN-Arab League envoy Kofi Annan.
The regime of President Bashar al-Assad has been cracking down on dissent since mid-March 2011 in violence the Observatory says has killed more than 10,000 people.
A former army commander who now leads a military council trying to organise armed resistance to Syrian President Bashar al-Assad said air strikes on forces spearheading his military crackdown would be the only way to avoid a protracted civil war.
Western and regional powers grappling with how to support the year-long uprising against Assad should shed a reluctance for military action and consider air strikes to force out the Alawite ruling elite, General Mustafa al-Sheikh told Reuters.
This would preserve the structure of the armed forces and incur less bloodshed than arming the mostly Sunni Muslim rebels, as advocated by Saudi Arabia and other Gulf states, the Sunni commander said.
“You will not need a long air campaign. Seventy percent of the Syrian military is already out of action and air strikes would be a message to the Syrian people that the international community is really with them,” he said, referring to Sunni soldiers who make up the bulk of the army and ten of thousands of whom are now confined to barracks.
Western powers have little appetite for military intervention in Syria and the NATO military alliance has ruled out a repeat of last year’s air campaign in support of rebels who toppled Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi.
Sheikh said chaos was brewing in Syria because many civilians were joining the rebels after their relatives were killed, imprisoned or tortured by Assad’s Alawite led-forces.
“They’re badly outgunned and still want revenge. They will be emboldened if they get serious weapons. Nothing will control them,” he said during an interview at a dusty camp for defecting Syrian officers near the border with Syria.
Sheikh pointed to people in a nearby tent paying condolences to an officer from Hama province. Twelve of his relatives were hacked to death in an attack by Alawite forces on the Sunni village of al-Latmana this week, Sheikh said
“How do you expect his family to react? What do you expect the relatives of those who were raped and tortured to do? The regime is inviting revenge,” Sheikh said.
Turkish Prime Minister Tayyip Erdogan accused Syrian President Bashar al-Assad of personal responsibility for killing civilians and said on Tuesday he would take unspecified steps after Syrian troops shot at refugees inside Turkey.
“He is continuing to kill 60, 70, 80, 100 every day,” Erdogan said of Assad, whom he once called a friend but whose troops were now, the Turkish premier said, “mercilessly” shooting fleeing women and children in the back.
Speaking in China before heading back to the region for talks with Arab power Saudi Arabia, another force pressing for Assad’s removal, Erdogan condemned the shooting on Monday which wounded three Syrians and two Turks in a frontier refugee camp.
“There was a very clear violation of the border. We are going to conduct a final assessment. Our diplomacy is continuing with the regional countries,” he said. “After that, of course, we will take the steps that need to be taken.”
He did not elaborate. Opposition from UN Security Council heavyweights Russia and China, as well as from Assad’s long-time backer Iran, argues against military intervention in support of the Syrian rebels by sympathetic regional and Western powers.
Libyan officials said on Tuesday that they are ready to put on trial remnants of the previous regime, including Muammar Gaddafi’s son Seif al-Islam who is wanted by the International Criminal Court.
“We are ready to carry out the trials of members of the former regime, be it those who are in the country or those who will be extradited,” Deputy Justice Minister Khalifa Ashur told journalists in Tripoli.
Libya is at loggerheads with the International Criminal Court over who has the right to bring former regime figures such as Seif-al Islam and the dead dictator’s spymaster, Abdullah Senussi, to justice.
“The International Criminal Court issued their arrest warrants during a war when our justice system was in shambles,” said Ashur in reference to last year’s conflict, adding that local courts are now ready to process such cases.
The ICC wants Seif al-Islam in The Hague to face charges of crimes against humanity for his role in battling the uprising against his father, but Libya’s new government wants to try him at home.
Ashur said that he had recently visited Gaddafi’s son, who has been held by a militia in Zintan, 180 kms (110 miles) south of Tripoli since his capture last November, and found him to be doing “well.”
He said his ministry is paving the way for Seif al-Islam’s transfer to an official detention centre in the capital where he will be tried by Libyan judges — a move that runs counter to the protests of rights groups.
Prime Minister Abdel Rahim al-Kib said international monitors were welcome to attend and oversee the legal proceedings.
“What we are trying to do is get to the point where we are reflective of the future Libya which has every respect for human rights,” he said.
Libya’s interim authorities have stopped paying bonuses to former rebels due to widespread fraud costing millions of Libyan dinars, the official LANA news agency reported on Monday.
“Payment of rewards to rebels has been stopped due to violations and abuses,” Mohammed Harizi, spokesman for the ruling National Transitional Council, was quoted as saying.
“Millions of (Libyan) dinars allocated to revolutionaries were lost in (illegitimate) payments to non-beneficiaries,” he said.
The interim government had been handing out cash payments of up to 4,000 Libyan dinars ($3,200) to civilians turned fighters who took on the forces of Muammar Gaddafi last year.
But the system — much like a scheme to finance the treatment of the country’s war wounded abroad — proved vulnerable to false claims.
Violations were referred to the offices of the attorney general and audit bureau for investigation, the spokesman said.
A bomb was thrown at a convoy carrying the head of the United Nations mission to Libya on Tuesday, a UN spokeswoman said, but no one was hurt in the explosion.
The attack in the eastern city of Benghazi is the first of its kind targeting a foreign mission since last year’s revolt overthrew Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi, and is likely to raise concerns about instability in the country.
“While on a visit to Benghazi the head of the UN support mission in Libya had what appeared to be an explosive device thrown at his convoy. No one has been hurt and the authorities are investigating,” said the UN’s Hua Jiang.
A security official who was traveling with the convoy, but declined to give his name, said the home-made device was thrown while the convoy’s five armored vehicles were pulling into the parking area of the Supreme Security Committee’s building, where they had a meeting scheduled.
DAMASCUS, April 10, (Agen-cies): Syrian forces on Tuesday pounded protest hubs in apparent breach of a ceasefire deal brokered by UN-Arab League envoy Kofi Annan, who appealed for his plan to be implemented without preconditions.
Syria said it was abiding by the plan, but Annan accused Damascus of pulling troops from some areas and moving them to others, and the rebel Free Syrian Army warned it would resume attacks if the government offensive does not stop.
Washington said it hoped the UN Security Council would consider action if Annan concludes that Damascus broke its commitments.
The violence drew sharp condemnation from France and Britain, with even Russia urging its ally to act more decisively to implement the truce.
Syrian Foreign Minister Walid Muallem said Damascus begun carrying out the Annan deal by pulling some troops out of certain provinces.
Annan, visiting Syrian refugees in Turkey, said that the Syrian army had indicated it was pulling out of some areas but he had also received reports of troops moving into other parts of the country.
“They have indicated that there has been withdrawals... but we also received indications from other sources that there are movements towards areas which have not been previously targeted,” he told reporters.
“I again appeal to the Syrian government and the Syrian parties to cease violence in accordance (with) the plan,” he told reporters. “I believe there should be no preconditions for stopping violence.”
The Annan plan has been under a cloud since Sunday, when Damascus said it would keep its side of the bargain only if rebels gave guarantees they would also stop fighting, a condition rejected out of hand.
Forces loyal to President Bashar al-Assad also shot four people in the village of Kfar Zeita in the central Hama province, but it was unclear if they were rebels or civilians.
Clashes also rocked the district of Mzeyreeb in the southern province of Daraa, where the dissent movement launched a year ago.
The Local Coordination Committees, one of the main opposition groups inside Syria, said “large military reinforcements” had arrived overnight on the eastern outskirts of Rastan in central Homs province.
The report could not be verified because of curbs on media activity.
Under the Annan deal, Syria was supposed to withdraw its forces from population centres on Tuesday ahead of a complete ceasefire on Thursday.
Activists say Syria has intensified its crackdown since the weekend when around 180 people were killed. On Monday, 105 died in one of the bloodiest days since mid-March last year.
Free Syrian Army spokesman Colonel Kassem Saadeddine warned that rebel forces would resume attacks on regular forces if they do not withdraw.
“If (the regime) does not stop shelling and not withdraw tanks, we will intensify our military operations and launch attacks,” he told AFP.
The head of the opposition Syrian National Council, Burhan Ghalioun, warned that his group, “as the legitimate representative of the people, will not allow the regime to use the (UN) plan as a licence to kill.”
But Muallem insisted Damascus had begun implementing the Annan plan.
“We have already withdrawn military units from different Syrian provinces,” he told a Moscow news conference after talks with Russian counterpart Sergei Lavrov.
Lavrov said Syria should be more decisive in fulfilling the Annan plan, which most notably calls on Syria to pull troops and weaponry out of cities hit by protests.
“We believe their actions could have been more active, more decisive when it comes to the implementation of the plan,” he said.
Lavrov later spoke with Annan by phone, telling him to put more pressure on the rebels to cooperate with his initiative.
He told Annan “the Syrian opposition and states that support it must take urgent measures to ensure a sustainable ceasefire,” and urged him “to step up his work with them along these lines,” the foreign ministry said.
White House spokesman Jay Carney said Washington had so far only seen evidence of further “brutality and aggression” from Assad’s forces.
“We would certainly hope the UN Security Council would evaluate the situation in Syria if in fact Mr Annan finds that the Assad regime has not abided by its own commitments to begin withdrawal by today,” Carney said.
Germany’s UN ambassador, Peter Wittig, said Syria has not complied with the plan and that international measures must be studied.
Assad “has not complied with the Annan plan; instead he has scaled up violence and human rights violations,” Wittig said.
There was equally tough language from London and Paris.
“There is no evidence so far that the Assad regime has any intention of adhering to any agreement it makes,” Britain’s Foreign Secretary William Hague said.
Syrian forces “have ruthlessly subjected whole communities to an inhumane campaign of shelling, forced expulsions and executions.
“All those with influence over the Syrian leadership, including Russia, have a duty to back efforts to stop the violence and to isolate a regime which is as doomed as it is dangerous to the Syrian people,” he added.
French foreign ministry spokesman Bernard Valero called Muallem’s assertion that Syria pulled troops out of some areas “a new expression of a flagrant and unacceptable lie.”
Damascus was also rebuked for violence that spilled over into its neighbours on Monday, killing a Lebanese TV cameraman inside Lebanon and wounding four people in a Turkish camp for Syrian refugees.
Turkish Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan accused Syria of a “clear violation” of common frontiers, while Lebanon demanded an investigation.
The United Nations says more than 9,000 people have been killed since anti-regime protests broke out in March 2011. Monitors put the number at more than 10,000.
Fifty-two people including 28 civilians were killed across Syria on Tuesday, the day the government was expected to pull its forces from protest hubs under a UN-Arab League peace plan, monitors said.
Among the dead were 19 members of the regime’s security forces and five rebels killed in fighting in several provinces, said the Syrian Observatory for Human Rights.
Six civilians were killed in bombardment of the Khaldiyeh district of Homs city in the centre of the country, and a seventh was shot dead in the Bab Tadmur neighbourhood.
In Hama province, also in central Syria, seven civilians were killed in Kfar Zeita, the scene of fierce clashes with rebels and aerial bombardment on Monday, the Britain-based monitoring group said.
Another four civilians were reported killed in Daraa province in the south, and a child was killed at Harasta near the capital, the Observatory said.
In Deir Ezzor, a civilian was killed by gunfire, while eight others were killed in the region of Aleppo. Five rebels were also reported killed in Daraa, Homs, Hama and Aleppo.
In addition, 11 soldiers were killed in the northeast region of Hassakeh, five in Aleppo province and three near the Turkish border.
The latest violence came as government forces were to have withdrawn from protest hubs under the peace plan drawn up by UN-Arab League envoy Kofi Annan.
The regime of President Bashar al-Assad has been cracking down on dissent since mid-March 2011 in violence the Observatory says has killed more than 10,000 people.
A former army commander who now leads a military council trying to organise armed resistance to Syrian President Bashar al-Assad said air strikes on forces spearheading his military crackdown would be the only way to avoid a protracted civil war.
Western and regional powers grappling with how to support the year-long uprising against Assad should shed a reluctance for military action and consider air strikes to force out the Alawite ruling elite, General Mustafa al-Sheikh told Reuters.
This would preserve the structure of the armed forces and incur less bloodshed than arming the mostly Sunni Muslim rebels, as advocated by Saudi Arabia and other Gulf states, the Sunni commander said.
“You will not need a long air campaign. Seventy percent of the Syrian military is already out of action and air strikes would be a message to the Syrian people that the international community is really with them,” he said, referring to Sunni soldiers who make up the bulk of the army and ten of thousands of whom are now confined to barracks.
Western powers have little appetite for military intervention in Syria and the NATO military alliance has ruled out a repeat of last year’s air campaign in support of rebels who toppled Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi.
Sheikh said chaos was brewing in Syria because many civilians were joining the rebels after their relatives were killed, imprisoned or tortured by Assad’s Alawite led-forces.
“They’re badly outgunned and still want revenge. They will be emboldened if they get serious weapons. Nothing will control them,” he said during an interview at a dusty camp for defecting Syrian officers near the border with Syria.
Sheikh pointed to people in a nearby tent paying condolences to an officer from Hama province. Twelve of his relatives were hacked to death in an attack by Alawite forces on the Sunni village of al-Latmana this week, Sheikh said
“How do you expect his family to react? What do you expect the relatives of those who were raped and tortured to do? The regime is inviting revenge,” Sheikh said.
Turkish Prime Minister Tayyip Erdogan accused Syrian President Bashar al-Assad of personal responsibility for killing civilians and said on Tuesday he would take unspecified steps after Syrian troops shot at refugees inside Turkey.
“He is continuing to kill 60, 70, 80, 100 every day,” Erdogan said of Assad, whom he once called a friend but whose troops were now, the Turkish premier said, “mercilessly” shooting fleeing women and children in the back.
Speaking in China before heading back to the region for talks with Arab power Saudi Arabia, another force pressing for Assad’s removal, Erdogan condemned the shooting on Monday which wounded three Syrians and two Turks in a frontier refugee camp.
“There was a very clear violation of the border. We are going to conduct a final assessment. Our diplomacy is continuing with the regional countries,” he said. “After that, of course, we will take the steps that need to be taken.”
He did not elaborate. Opposition from UN Security Council heavyweights Russia and China, as well as from Assad’s long-time backer Iran, argues against military intervention in support of the Syrian rebels by sympathetic regional and Western powers.
Libyan officials said on Tuesday that they are ready to put on trial remnants of the previous regime, including Muammar Gaddafi’s son Seif al-Islam who is wanted by the International Criminal Court.
“We are ready to carry out the trials of members of the former regime, be it those who are in the country or those who will be extradited,” Deputy Justice Minister Khalifa Ashur told journalists in Tripoli.
Libya is at loggerheads with the International Criminal Court over who has the right to bring former regime figures such as Seif-al Islam and the dead dictator’s spymaster, Abdullah Senussi, to justice.
“The International Criminal Court issued their arrest warrants during a war when our justice system was in shambles,” said Ashur in reference to last year’s conflict, adding that local courts are now ready to process such cases.
The ICC wants Seif al-Islam in The Hague to face charges of crimes against humanity for his role in battling the uprising against his father, but Libya’s new government wants to try him at home.
Ashur said that he had recently visited Gaddafi’s son, who has been held by a militia in Zintan, 180 kms (110 miles) south of Tripoli since his capture last November, and found him to be doing “well.”
He said his ministry is paving the way for Seif al-Islam’s transfer to an official detention centre in the capital where he will be tried by Libyan judges — a move that runs counter to the protests of rights groups.
Prime Minister Abdel Rahim al-Kib said international monitors were welcome to attend and oversee the legal proceedings.
“What we are trying to do is get to the point where we are reflective of the future Libya which has every respect for human rights,” he said.
Libya’s interim authorities have stopped paying bonuses to former rebels due to widespread fraud costing millions of Libyan dinars, the official LANA news agency reported on Monday.
“Payment of rewards to rebels has been stopped due to violations and abuses,” Mohammed Harizi, spokesman for the ruling National Transitional Council, was quoted as saying.
“Millions of (Libyan) dinars allocated to revolutionaries were lost in (illegitimate) payments to non-beneficiaries,” he said.
The interim government had been handing out cash payments of up to 4,000 Libyan dinars ($3,200) to civilians turned fighters who took on the forces of Muammar Gaddafi last year.
But the system — much like a scheme to finance the treatment of the country’s war wounded abroad — proved vulnerable to false claims.
Violations were referred to the offices of the attorney general and audit bureau for investigation, the spokesman said.
A bomb was thrown at a convoy carrying the head of the United Nations mission to Libya on Tuesday, a UN spokeswoman said, but no one was hurt in the explosion.
The attack in the eastern city of Benghazi is the first of its kind targeting a foreign mission since last year’s revolt overthrew Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi, and is likely to raise concerns about instability in the country.
“While on a visit to Benghazi the head of the UN support mission in Libya had what appeared to be an explosive device thrown at his convoy. No one has been hurt and the authorities are investigating,” said the UN’s Hua Jiang.
A security official who was traveling with the convoy, but declined to give his name, said the home-made device was thrown while the convoy’s five armored vehicles were pulling into the parking area of the Supreme Security Committee’s building, where they had a meeting scheduled.
</text>
</article>