<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>6966</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/aljazeera-en-3dc5a8f9c0cfd58e6c71e7af58950f87.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g49</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/10/2012 12:33:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>At least 15 people have been killed and 28 wounded by two separate suicide bombs in Herat and Helmand provinces in Afghanistan. A government building and a police compound were the targets.
Two separate suicide bomb attacks have killed at least 15 people in the  provinces of Herat, in the west of Afghanistan, and Helmand in the south.
In Herat, two suicide bombers detonated explosives as they were driving their vehicle into a government compound. Police tried to stop them, but could not stop the explosion.
"There were two individuals in the car, one was wearing a burqa. One of the bombers is totally shattered and the other person's body is still there with his [suicide] vest still unexploded," provincial police chief Sayed Agha Saqeb said. The dead included two policemen, an intelligence officer and six civilians, according to Saqeb.
The attack occurred between Herat city, the provincial capital, and the main airport in the area in the district of Guzara.
In the Helmand attack, the bombers were intercepted trying to enter a police station in the Musa Qala district, said Daud Ahmadi, a spokesman for the provincial governor.
"One of the bombers was spotted by the police and shot dead," Ahmadi said. "Two others managed to enter and blow themselves up at the office."
The Taliban claimed responsibility for the Helmand attack, saying it had been targeting the district governor and police chief, as well as other government officials.
ng/msh (AP, dpa, Reuters, AFP)
Norwegian mass murderer Anders Breivik is not criminally insane, according to a new psychiatric assessment, which contradicts an earlier examination. It comes six days before Breivik is to go on trial on terror charges.
The European Court of Human Rights has approved a long-standing request from the British government to extradite five terror suspects to the US. Radical cleric Abu Hamza al-Masri is among the detainees.
Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov asked Syria to implement international envoy Kofi Annan's peace plan, while also calling for the international community to press Syrian opposition groups to cease fire.
At least 15 people have been killed and 28 wounded by two separate suicide bombs in Herat and Helmand provinces in Afghanistan. A government building and a police compound were the targets.
</text>
</article>