<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>11066</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/panarmenian-en-dfb9e455f7dd9d4c69ce3f9aeaf12184.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1125</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/16/2012 2:14:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Explore news, videos, and much more based on what your friends are reading and watching. Publish your own activity and retain full control.
Oil prices slipped on Monday after &amp;hellip;
Oil prices slipped on Monday after nuclear talks over the weekend between major crude producer Iran and world powers eased concerns over Middle East supplies, analysts said.
Brent North Sea crude for delivery in June fell $1.16 to stand at $120.05 in London midday deals.
New York's main contract, West Texas Intermediate crude for May, dropped 32 cents to $102.55 a barrel.
"Oil has slipped after 'constructive' talks between Iran and six of the world's biggest economic superpowers," said IG Markets analysts Justin Harper.
"This has helped take some of the 'war premium' out of energy prices," added the Singapore-based strategist.
Saturday's nuclear talks between officials from Iran and diplomats from the so-called P5+1 group comprising the United States, Russia, China, Britain, France and Germany have largely been described as "positive" by both sides.
However Western officials have stressed that a great deal was expected of the Islamic republic at the next meeting in Baghdad on May 23.
"The weekend discussions between the P5+1 group and Iran suggest that Iran is being constructive enough to avoid any US/Israeli rush to judgement," said PVM brokers analyst David Hufton.
"Sanctions and the threat of an Israeli strike may be achieving their aim."
The weekend talks were aimed at persuading Tehran -- the second-biggest producer of crude in OPEC -- to halt its controversial nuclear programme, which much of the international community believes is geared towards building an atomic weapon.
Iran has so far insisted that it is enriching uranium for peaceful purposes including cancer treatment.
Several rounds of financial sanctions by the UN Security Council, the United States and the European Union have so far been ineffective in pressuring Iran to cease its nuclear activities.
The Islamic republic has previously threatened to shut the strategic Strait of Hormuz -- a major passageway for a fifth of the world's global oil supply -- if it faced further sanctions.
Meanwhile, a decline in the euro against other major currencies on renewed concerns about the eurozone's fiscal problems was also weighing on the crude market, analysts said.
A weaker euro makes dollar-priced oil more expensive, dampening demand and pushing prices lower.
Are Oil Prices the Biggest Risk to the &amp;hellip;
FILE -A file satellite image taken Sunday &amp;hellip;
Brent oil prices slip on weak US, China &amp;hellip;
Congressman says no to war in Iran
Six worst home fixes for the money
How to avoid mortifying date moments
'Titanic' film achieves very rare feat
Norway mass killer defiant as trial begins
KABUL (Reuters) - Afghan President Hamid Karzai said on Monday that a coordinated Taliban attack showed a "failure" by Afghan intelligence and especially by NATO, as heavy street fighting between insurgents &amp;hellip; More »Karzai says NATO failed as 18-hr Kabul attack ends
KABUL (Reuters) - Afghan President Hamid Karzai said on Monday that a coordinated Taliban attack showed a "failure" by Afghan intelligence and especially by NATO, as heavy street fighting between insurgents and security forces came to an end after 18 hours. Battles which broke out at midday on Sunday gripped the city's &amp;hellip;
OSLO (Reuters) - The Norwegian far-right militant who massacred 77 people last summer gave a clenched-fist salute, smirked at the court and pleaded not guilty on the first day of a trial that threatens &amp;hellip; More »Smirking Norway killer Breivik pleads not guilty
OSLO (Reuters) - The Norwegian far-right militant who massacred 77 people last summer gave a clenched-fist salute, smirked at the court and pleaded not guilty on the first day of a trial that threatens to turn into a "circus" showcasing his anti-Islamic views. Anders Behring Breivik, 33, has said he acted in defense of &amp;hellip;
BEIRUT (Reuters) - A handful of soldiers in blue caps put a tentative United Nations presence on the ground in Syria on Monday, predicting success for their mission to stabilize a shaky four-day-old ceasefire &amp;hellip; More »As shells fall, U.N. few say can save Syria truce
BEIRUT (Reuters) - A handful of soldiers in blue caps put a tentative United Nations presence on the ground in Syria on Monday, predicting success for their mission to stabilize a shaky four-day-old ceasefire even as shells continued to fall. Charged with overseeing an end to 13 months of violence, the unarmed multinational &amp;hellip;
DUBAI (Reuters) - Iran is ready to resolve all nuclear issues in the next round of talks with world powers if the West starts lifting sanctions, its foreign minister said on Monday. In an interview with &amp;hellip; More »Iran says ready to resolve nuclear issues
DUBAI (Reuters) - Iran is ready to resolve all nuclear issues in the next round of talks with world powers if the West starts lifting sanctions, its foreign minister said on Monday. In an interview with the Iranian student news agency ISNA, Ali Akbar Salehi also hinted that Iran could make concessions on its higher-grade &amp;hellip;
(Reuters) - Gunmen killed four Shi'ite farmers in the northern outskirts of Baghdad on Monday, police and hospital sources said, in the latest attack to highlight underlying sectarian and ethnic tensions &amp;hellip; More »Gunmen kill four Shi'ite farmers in Baghdad attack
(Reuters) - Gunmen killed four Shi'ite farmers in the northern outskirts of Baghdad on Monday, police and hospital sources said, in the latest attack to highlight underlying sectarian and ethnic tensions in Iraq. Violence in Iraq has declined since the height of sectarian conflict in 2006-07, but bombings and shootings &amp;hellip;
Get breaking news, videos, blogs and more at ABC News. More »Breaking News from ABC News
Syrian rebels caught embellishing on tape. More »Syria’s video activists
View the latest slideshow galleries on Yahoo! News. More »Photos of the day
These flexible online degrees could help you go to school on your terms.
Thinking about going back to school? Find out which online degrees rank highest in popularity.
</text>
</article>