<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>31539</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/irishexaminer-9f7e8eb64b8addd3bbb80c1e474b2cf9.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g159</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/27/2012 9:28:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Welcome back,   (log out?)
Damascus has refuted accusations of being behind a ruthless attack in Houla where over 90 civilians were killed. Political analyst Ibrahim Alloush told RT those killed were actually Assad loyalists, and the timing is suspicious.
UN monitors have confirmed that the bloodshed in Houla has left at least 90 people dead, including 32 children. Damascus denies government forces were involved, but the international community has been quick to decry Assad amid calls for his ouster.
Admitting that the chances for negotiations between the Syrian authorities and the political opposition remain slim, Russia’s Deputy Foreign Minister added that the world’s premier terrorist group is responsible for wreaking havoc in the Arab Republic.
At least 55 people have been killed and 372 others injured by two powerful blasts in the Syrian capital on Thursday morning. The car bombs detonated near a military intelligence building.
Polling stations have closed in Syria, where people were voting for a 250-strong parliament in the first democratic election in decades. More than 7,000 candidates, including 710 women, were competing for the seats.
Kofi Annan has said the situation in Syria is "bleak," expressing concern at reports the government was still conducting military operations. But experts say the West’s biased approach is to blame for that.
Published: 27 May, 2012, 23:00
John Moore / Getty Images / AFP
The UN Security Council has convened for an urgent session in New York to hear a report over the shelling in Syria's Houla, which killed at least 90 people on Friday. Britain and France are pressing for a statement condemning the Syrian government.
­Norwegian General Robert Mood, who heads the UN observer mission in Syria, tells the Assembly 116 people were killed, 300  injured in massacre in Houla, reports Reuters.
There are concerns that most “civilians killed in Houla were victims of a blatant murder: they were either shot in the temple from a short distance, or their throats were cut,” Russia’s UN envoy deputy Aleksandr Pankin told journalists before the session began.
“Very few of the people who died in Houla were killed by artillery shelling,” he added.
At the same time, the 15 members of the UNSC are considering a French-British statement condemning “in the strongest possible terms, government forces for Houla massacre in Syria.” The press statement would say that the “indiscriminate and disproportionate use of force” against civilians was in “flagrant violation” of international law, UN resolutions and the Syrian government’s own commitment to a ceasefire.
The statement would also demand the government cease the use of heavy weapons in residential centers and immediately pull back troops from such areas, reports Kuwaiti news agency KUNA.
UN Security Council statements are issued by consensus.  These statements, presidential or to the press, are non-binding. Presidential statements are drawn if a  resolution cannot be passed, and are meant as a warning that the  Council is paying attention to the situation and further action may  follow.
Russia opposes putting all the blame on  forces loyal to President Bashar al-Assad, say sources in the Council. Moscow wants to introduce references to “a third party,” implying terrorist groups such as al-Qaeda could be behind the attack in western Syria.
"The tragic events in Syria and the  deaths of dozens of people deserve condemnation. However it is necessary  to seriously examine the causes of what happened," Russia's Deputy Foreign  Minister Gennady Gatilov said on Twitter.
The Syrian government denies involvement in the massacre. Damascus condemned the attack Saturday, saying “terrorist” groups were behind it.
Initially the massacre was reported by opposition activists, who claimed that the city was shelled by government forces during an anti-regime demonstration. Reports also suggested that troops entered the city, butchering dozens of people.
A team of UN observers arriving in Houla to investigate the killings said the casualties included 32 children under the age of 10 and dozens of women. Russia hopes the Sunday report by General Mood will bring some clarity to the incident.
Syria is trying to implement a peace plan drawn by UN special envoy Koffi Annan. The plan is meant to stop bloodshed in the country, which has been trapped in a violent civil turmoil for over a year. The popular uprising against President Assad’s regime has taken over 9,000 lives, the UN estimates. Assad says he is a fighting foreign insurgency.
Annan’s plan demands a ceasefire from all parties to the conflict starting on April 10, 2012, and deployment of a UN observing mission. The massacre in Houla comes as the biggest incident since the observer mission began. Now the Free Syrian Army, the biggest opposition force fighting Assad’s troops, says it will pull out of the plan “unless the UN Security Council takes urgent steps for the protection of civilians.”
Damascus has refuted accusations of being behind a ruthless attack in Houla where over 90 civilians were killed. Political analyst Ibrahim Alloush told RT those killed were actually Assad loyalists, and the timing is suspicious.
Leon Panetta has stated that the US is ready to do everything it can to prevent Iran from developing a nuclear weapon. The American envoy to Israel earlier said that the military option is “fully available” and the necessary planning has been done.
Indiscriminate and Disproportionate Force ?? Now that's rich, Israel does this all the time on Gaza, remember Operation Cast Lead a few years ago ?? Not that I condone massacres or something but where was the UN Security Council back then ?? Where were the sanctions against Israel ?? Looks more like the western powere really want a pretext to bomb Damascus like they bombed Tripoli in Libya if you ask me...
RT, can you please put on some new programs for the weekend? You literally repeat the SAME EXACT news with no new stories every hour, and the same other program (sports, documentary, etc.) every two hours. How do you want to get viewers with that kind of lineup? What's the point of paying someone to be in the studio to say the news live when you can just replay the same newscast 12 times a day anyway?
How come when I wait for the RT page to load, the status bar on my browser says "Waiting for Reddit to load" ???
        &amp;copy; Autonomous Nonprofit Organization "TV-Novosti", 2005-2012. All rights reserved.
</text>
</article>