<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>3857</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/montrealgazette-eb6582b8e7e6c5ece8b15fa054a36a2d.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g142</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/2/2012 6:12:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Syrian government troops clashed with rebel forces across the country today as international envoy Kofi Annan briefed the United Nations Security Council on his efforts to ease the crisis.
A flurry of high-level diplomacy has failed to stop the violence in a year-old conflict that the UN says has killed more than 9,000 people, and at least one senior emissary at the UN says it could be "months" before there is peace.
Syria's government must take the first step toward settling the country's conflict by pulling troops from city streets, Russia's foreign minister said Monday, raising pressure on an old ally. While Sergey Lavrov added that opposition forces should quickly follow suit and withdraw too, his statement appeared to reflect Moscow's increasing impatience with Syrian President Bashar al-Assad. Russia and China have twice shielded Assad from UN sanctions over his crackdown on an uprising in which more than 9,000 people have been killed. But Moscow also has strongly supported a plan to settle the crisis by Kofi Annan, the joint UN and Arab League envoy for Syria. "The Syrian government must take the first step and start the troop withdrawal in line with Kofi Annan's plan," Lavrov said. Lavrov's statement challenged the stance taken by the Syrian government, which has said it wouldn't withdraw forces from towns and cities until life returns to normal.
On Sunday, more than 70 countries, including the United States, pledged to send millions of dollars and communications equipment to opposition groups inside Syria. The measure appeared to signal a growing belief that diplomacy and sanctions alone will not push Syrian President Bashar al-Assad from power and end his regime’s repression of the uprising against it.
Participants at an international diplomatic conference in Istanbul said Saudi Arabia and other Gulf countries are also creating a fund to pay Syrian rebels fighters and soldiers who defect from the regime. One delegate described the fund as a "pot of gold" to undermine Assad's army.
Participants confirmed the Gulf plan on condition of anonymity because details were still being worked out. One said the fund would involve several million dollars a month. It is said to be earmarked for salaries, but it was not clear whether there would be any effort to prevent the money from being used to buy arms, an issue that could prompt stronger accusations of military meddling.
Anti-regime activists inside Syria welcomed the news, while worrying that the aid would be too little, too late.
"This is what we have been asking for, but if they had decided to do this months ago, we could have avoided a large number of martyrs," said Fadi al-Yassin from the northern province of Idlib. "We know that there is no way to topple the regime without force."
As the joint UN-Arab League envoy, Annan has been pushing a six-point plan to end the country's crisis that includes an immediate daily two-hour halt to fighting so aid can reach suffering civilians. It also calls for an overall ceasefire so all parties can discuss a political solution.
Annan began briefing the UN Security Council in New York on his progress Monday at 10 a.m. ET. Delegates entering the closed-door briefing were unusually tight-lipped with reporters, CBC's Melissa Kent said, though U.S. Ambassador Susan Rice was expected to hold a news conference afterward.
One official who spoke on condition of anonymity said the violence in Syria could continue for months.
"A senior diplomat, a member of the Security Council, told me that this kind of situation, a ceasefire and end to the violence, it’s not like a schoolyard brawl. You can’t just pull the two sides apart or order them to stop fighting, and this process will take … weeks if not months," Kent said.
The Syrian government has said it accepts his plan while rejecting some of the steps it requires, like withdrawing its troops from towns and cities. Its attacks on opposition areas have continued unabated.
The opposition has also rejected dialogue with the regime, saying it has killed too many people to be part of a solution to the crisis.
Violence continued in Syria Monday.
The Britain-based Syrian Observatory for Human Rights said three civilians, five rebels and one government soldier were killed in clashes in the northern Idlib province.
In the northern city of Aleppo, explosives stashed in a kiosk blew up, killing one person, the group said, while rebels in the south killed two soldiers at a checkpoint.
Government forces stormed the southern town of Dael, raiding activist homes and setting some on fire, the Observatory said. Another group, the Local Coordination Committees, said more than 20 homes had been damaged.
Residents could not be reached for comment and activists' claims could not be independently verified. The Syrian government rarely comments on specific incidents and bars most media from working inside the country.
Syria's uprising began in March 2011 as part of the Arab Spring, with peaceful protests calling for political reforms. Assad's regime sent tanks, snipers and thugs to try to quash the revolt, and many in the opposition have taken up arms to defend themselves and attack government troops.
</text>
</article>