<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>11228</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/panarmenian-en-dfb9e455f7dd9d4c69ce3f9aeaf12184.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1125</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/16/2012 5:49:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Explore news, videos, and much more based on what your friends are reading and watching. Publish your own activity and retain full control.
Iran's Russian-built nuclear reactor &amp;hellip;
Iranian Foreign Minister Ali Akbar &amp;hellip;
Iran on Monday called on the West to look to lifting its sanctions if it wants to quickly resolve the showdown over Tehran's disputed nuclear activities, and hinted it could make concessions on uranium enrichment in return.
Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Salehi outlined that message in an interview with the news agency ISNA following milestone talks at the weekend in Istanbul between Iran and world powers.
Those talks, described by both sides as an encouraging revival of a process that had been moribund for 15 months, are now due to be developed in another, more substantive round on May 23 in Baghdad.
"If the West wants to build trust, it should begin with sanctions, because it can help speed up the talks reaching a solution," Salehi was quoted as saying.
"If goodwill (from the West) is present... we are ready to rapidly and easily, and even in the Baghdad meeting, resolve all issues" regarding Iran's nuclear programme, he said.
The foreign minister appeared to suggest that the level of enrichment could be up for discussion.
While Iran's negotiators will take the position in Baghdad that producing 20 percent enriched uranium "is our right," Salehi said, if the world powers "guarantee they will provide us with fuel of various purities, it will change the perspective."
Under those conditions, Salehi added, "we can engage in the talks and negotiate on how to obtain uranium with different purity."
In a separate interview with state satellite channel Jam-e Jam, Salehi noted that "enrichment covers a wide range, from natural uranium to 100 percent enrichment, so one can talk within this spectrum."
Iran currently enriches uranium to 3.5 percent and to 20 percent. The former it says is to power its Bushehr nuclear electricity plant and the latter it says is to generate medical isotopes in its Tehran research reactor.
Uranium has to be enriched to 90 percent or above for use in an atomic bomb.
Salehi's comments could add impetus to the Baghdad round of talks, especially as the West has so far made no mention of previous demands that Iran halt all uranium enrichment -- a demand also stated in UN Security Council resolutions.
However, the question of the West reducing its sanctions on Iran seemed remote at this point of the discussions.
The sanctions, sharply ramped up this year, target Iran's all-important oil export sector and are seen by many Western capitals as a key reason why Tehran was willing to resume its negotiations with the so-called P5+1 group comprising the five permanent UN Security Council members plus Germany.
By the beginning of July, the United States and the European Union are due to fully implement economic sanctions they have already started -- unless some sort of breakthrough is made in the talks.
US President Barack Obama said on Sunday that "so far at least we haven't given away anything -- other than the opportunity for us to negotiate."
Speaking to reporters after an Americas summit in Colombia, Obama said: "The clock is ticking and I've been very clear to Iran and our negotiating partners that we're not going to have these talks just drag out in a stalling process."
The United States and many of its EU allies believe that Iran has been working towards developing a nuclear weapons capability -- a suspicion given weight by the UN's International Atomic Energy Agency.
But Iran insists that its nuclear programme is entirely peaceful, and its supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, has called the possession of atomic weapons "a great sin."
Can we stop Iran from getting nukes &amp;hellip;
FILE - In this Tuesday, June 21, 2011 &amp;hellip;
Iran says ready to resolve nuclear  &amp;hellip;
Iran's Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali &amp;hellip;
Worst U.S. airports for connections
Rally driver tests new BMW convertible
Awkward confrontation during NBA game
Norway mass killer defiant as trial begins
UNITED NATIONS (Reuters) - The U.N. Security Council on Monday strongly condemned North Korea's rocket launch, urged tightening of existing U.N. sanctions and warned of further action if Pyongyang carries &amp;hellip; More »U.N. condemns North Korea launch, warns on nuclear test
UNITED NATIONS (Reuters) - The U.N. Security Council on Monday strongly condemned North Korea's rocket launch, urged tightening of existing U.N. sanctions and warned of further action if Pyongyang carries out another missile launch or nuclear test. China, a permanent veto-wielding council member and North Korea's protector &amp;hellip;
OSLO (Reuters) - The Norwegian far-right gunman who massacred 77 people last summer gave a clenched-fist salute, smirked at the court and pleaded not guilty on the first day of a trial that threatens to &amp;hellip; More »Smirking Norway killer Breivik pleads not guilty
OSLO (Reuters) - The Norwegian far-right gunman who massacred 77 people last summer gave a clenched-fist salute, smirked at the court and pleaded not guilty on the first day of a trial that threatens to turn into a "circus" showcasing his anti-Islamic views. Anders Behring Breivik, 33, has said he acted in defense of his &amp;hellip;
BEIRUT (Reuters) - A handful of soldiers in blue caps put a tentative United Nations presence at the heart of the Syrian crisis on Monday, predicting success for their mission to stabilize a shaky four-day-old &amp;hellip; More »Shelling, shaky truce challenge U.N. few in Syria
BEIRUT (Reuters) - A handful of soldiers in blue caps put a tentative United Nations presence at the heart of the Syrian crisis on Monday, predicting success for their mission to stabilize a shaky four-day-old ceasefire even as shells were still falling. Charged with overseeing an end to 13 months of violence, the unarmed &amp;hellip;
KABUL (Reuters) - Afghan President Hamid Karzai said on Monday that a coordinated Taliban attack showed a "failure" by Afghan intelligence and especially by NATO, as heavy street fighting between insurgents &amp;hellip; More »Karzai says NATO failed as 18 hour Kabul attack ends
KABUL (Reuters) - Afghan President Hamid Karzai said on Monday that a coordinated Taliban attack showed a "failure" by Afghan intelligence and especially by NATO, as heavy street fighting between insurgents and security forces came to an end after 18 hours. Battles which broke out at midday on Sunday gripped the city's &amp;hellip;
DUBAI (Reuters) - Iran is ready to resolve all nuclear issues in the next round of talks with world powers if the West starts lifting sanctions, its foreign minister said on Monday. In an interview with &amp;hellip; More »Iran says ready to resolve nuclear issues
DUBAI (Reuters) - Iran is ready to resolve all nuclear issues in the next round of talks with world powers if the West starts lifting sanctions, its foreign minister said on Monday. In an interview with the Iranian student news agency ISNA, Ali Akbar Salehi also hinted that Iran could make concessions on its higher-grade &amp;hellip;
Get breaking news, videos, blogs and more at ABC News. More »Breaking News from ABC News
How the Supreme Court’s decision on health care could limit government for a generation. More »A bigger case
Credit card companies offer huge bonuses. More »If you have stellar credit
These flexible online degrees could help you go to school on your terms.
Thinking about going back to school? Find out which online degrees rank highest in popularity.
</text>
</article>