<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>12717</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/independent-ie-72fd1950feb1027f88f74c4dd5db43dd.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g421</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/19/2012 2:07:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Explore news, videos, and much more based on what your friends are reading and watching. Publish your own activity and retain full control.
Colonel Ahmed Himmiche, leader &amp;hellip;
Syria on Thursday signed a preliminary accord outlining a protocol for a UN mission to monitor a fragile week-old ceasefire in the strife-torn country, the two sides announced.
Deputy Foreign Minister Faisal al-Mekdad signed the deal with a member of a UN advance team, the ministry said in a statement.
"This agreement comes within the framework of Syrian efforts aimed at making the Annan plan succeed and to facilitate the UN observer mission while respecting Syria's sovereignty," the statement said.
A spokesman for UN-Arab League envoy Kofi Annan, who drafted the six-point ceasefire accord, confirmed in Geneva that an agreement had been concluded between the two parties.
"This agreement outlines the functions of the observers as they fulfil their mandate in Syria and the tasks and responsibilities of the Syrian government in this regard," Ahmad Fawzi said in a statement.
"An effective observer team on the ground is vital if the lives of ordinary Syrian families are to slowly return to normal."
He added that discussions were under way with members of the Syrian opposition to ensure they also comply with the ceasefire.
"The hard part lies ahead, a truly Syrian-led and -owned political dialogue to address the legitimate concerns and aspirations of the Syrian people," Fawzi said.
The protocol will pave the way for some 300 UN observers to fan across the country to monitor a week-old truce aimed at ending 13 months of violence in Syria that the United Nations says has killed well over 9,000 people.
UN chief Ban Ki-moon earlier called for an expanded UN ceasefire observation mission to be sent to Syria even though he says President Bashar al-Assad has failed to end the violence.
The UN chief called for 300 unarmed observers to be sent on a three-month mission, in a report to be discussed by the UN Security Council later Thursday.
U.N.-Arab League special envoy Annan &amp;hellip;
Arab ministers urge Syria to open up &amp;hellip;
Bahrain's Foreign Minister Sheikh Khaled &amp;hellip;
Truce monitors aim to keep Syria peace &amp;hellip;
How you knew your dog or cat was 'the one'
14-year-old's movie-trailer voice stuns Web
U.S. Muslim claims FBI ordered his torture
Guide to beating a heart attack
UNITED NATIONS/PARIS (Reuters) - Syria has not fully withdrawn troops and heavy weapons from towns, failing to send a "clear signal" about its commitment to peace, U.N. chief Ban Ki-moon said on Thursday, &amp;hellip; More »U.N. head says Syria yet to send clear signal on peace
UNITED NATIONS/PARIS (Reuters) - Syria has not fully withdrawn troops and heavy weapons from towns, failing to send a "clear signal" about its commitment to peace, U.N. chief Ban Ki-moon said on Thursday, underlining Western fears for the week-old truce. In the first progress report since the Security Council passed a resolution &amp;hellip;
BHUBANESWAR, India (Reuters) - India successfully test-fired on Thursday a nuclear-capable missile that can reach Beijing and Eastern Europe, thrusting the emerging Asian power into a small club of nations &amp;hellip; More »India tests nuclear-capable missile that can reach China
BHUBANESWAR, India (Reuters) - India successfully test-fired on Thursday a nuclear-capable missile that can reach Beijing and Eastern Europe, thrusting the emerging Asian power into a small club of nations that can deploy nuclear weapons at such a great distance. Footage showed the rocket with a range of more than 5,000 &amp;hellip;
BAGHDAD (Reuters) - More than 20 bombs hit cities and towns across Iraq on Thursday, killing at least 36 and wounding more than 100, police and hospital sources said, raising fears of sectarian strife &amp;hellip; More »At least 36 killed in wave of Iraq blasts
BAGHDAD (Reuters) - More than 20 bombs hit cities and towns across Iraq on Thursday, killing at least 36 and wounding more than 100, police and hospital sources said, raising fears of sectarian strife in a country keen to show it can now maintain security. In Baghdad, three car bombs, two roadside bombs and one suicide &amp;hellip;
YANGON (Reuters) - Aung San Suu Kyi's planned debut in Myanmar's parliament next week could be shelved amid a standoff between her party and the government over one word used in the swearing-in oath for &amp;hellip; More »Myanmar oath standoff puts Suu Kyi's MP debut in doubt
YANGON (Reuters) - Aung San Suu Kyi's planned debut in Myanmar's parliament next week could be shelved amid a standoff between her party and the government over one word used in the swearing-in oath for new lawmakers. Newly elected MPs from Suu Kyi's National League for Democracy (NLD) party see the oath in its present &amp;hellip;
KABUL (Reuters) - The American ambassador to Afghanistan said on Thursday there was "no question" that the Haqqani network mounted attacks on Kabul and other areas over the weekend, and reiterated a long-standing &amp;hellip; More »Haqqani network behind Afghan attacks: U.S. envoy
KABUL (Reuters) - The American ambassador to Afghanistan said on Thursday there was "no question" that the Haqqani network mounted attacks on Kabul and other areas over the weekend, and reiterated a long-standing demand that ally Pakistan go after the group. The Afghan Taliban claimed responsibility for the attacks on foreign &amp;hellip;
Get breaking news, videos, blogs and more at ABC News. More »Breaking News from ABC News
Syrian rebels caught embellishing on tape. More »Syria’s video activists
View the latest slideshow galleries on Yahoo! News. More »Photos of the day
These flexible online degrees could help you go to school on your terms.
Thinking about going back to school? Find out which online degrees rank highest in popularity.
</text>
</article>