<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>12598</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/AP-71ac26b2886e2788491329ae88af5710.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g147</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>4/19/2012 10:38:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>BAQUBA, Iraq, April 19 (Xinhua) -- At least three people were killed and some 33 others wounded in separate bomb and gunfire attacks in Iraq's eastern province of Diyala on Thursday, a provincial police source said.
One of the attacks took place when a suicide bomber blew up his explosive vest outside the house of a police officer in al-Amin district in the provincial capital city of Baquba, some 65 km northeast of Baghdad, killing a passer-by and wounding 11 people, the source told Xinhua on condition of anonymity.
The officer survived the attack unharmed as he was not at home, but five of his family members were among the wounded, the source said.
In a separate incident, gunmen attacked a police checkpoint in al-Hadeed area, just west of Baquba and killed a policeman and wounded three others, the source added.
In addition, gunmen wearing military uniforms stormed a house of a member of the government-backed Awakening Council group in the town of Mansouriyat al-Jabal, some 45 km east of Baquba, killing him before they fled the scene, he said.
The Awakening Council group, or Sahwa in Arabic, consists of armed groups, including some former anti-U.S. Sunni insurgent groups which turned their guns against al-Qaida militants after the U.S.-led invasion of Iraq.
Also in the Diyala, 19 people were wounded in separate bomb attacks across the province mostly targeted the Iraqi security forces, the source added.
Diyala province, which stretches from the eastern edges of Baghdad to the Iranian border east of the country, has long been a stronghold for al-Qaida militants and other insurgent groups since the U.S.-led invasion of Iraq in 2003.
Earlier, the police reported that series of bomb attacks struck Baghdad and Salahudin province on Thursday morning, killing a total of 28 people and wounding of 77 others.
Special Report: Situation in Iraq
</text>
</article>