<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>199</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/nowlebanon-f5f297f60807ba3b5bd94447d9cf01b2.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g608</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>11/18/2011 5:03:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>DAMASCUS, Nov. 18 (Xinhua) -- Syria's Foreign Minister Walid al- Moallem suggested modifications over the Arab League's (AL) deal on the observer mission to Syria, said a statement issued by the AL on Friday.
The AL chief Nabil al-Arabi received a letter on Thursday from the Syrian foreign minister in which Syria proposed modifications on the Arab observer mission.
The AL is studying the modifications suggested by the Syrian side, according to the statement.
The Arab League issued Wednesday in Rabat, Morocco, a draft deal on the Arab mission of 500 observers to Syria and gave the Syrian government three days to sign it after it suspended Syria's membership in the pan-Arab body.
Syria claimed the suspension was illegal, but said it still intended to implement the Arab peace plan which it accepted on Nov. 2 to end its eight-month-long protests. The violence in Syria has left more than 3,500 dead, according to UN figures.
Meanwhile, a key opposition activist group said that 14 people were killed in several Syrian cities during new Friday's protests.
The Local Coordination Committees, a key Syrian activist network, said 14 people, including a child, were killed during Friday's protests. However, the account could not be verified in the absence of official comments.
Syria's state-run TV said that pro-government rallies erupted in several areas on Friday, including a main square in the capital of Damascus and the coastal province of Latakia, to express discontent with Syria's suspension from the AL.
Three law-enforcement members were killed and an officer was injured on Friday when an explosive device went off in the central province of Hama, according to Syrian state media.
</text>
</article>