<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>1944</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/hr/news-yahoo-fe8138b9f1da91b515ba71c6d3a6c137.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g1029</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>12/6/2011 4:21:00 PM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Death toll at Abul Fazl shrine could be as high as 48, say police, after suicide bomber targets Shia pilgrims
Dozens of people have been killed when a suicide bomber attacked a packed shrine in Kabul on one of the most important days in the Shia calender.
Witnesses said the bomber carried a backpack full of explosives into the crowd of worshippers outside the Abul Fazl shrine before detonating the device on Tuesday. The shrine was packed with Shia worshippers who had gathered for Ashura, the Shia Muslim holiday marking the death of Hussein ibn Ali, the grandson of the prophet Muhammad.
Kabul police said 48 people had died and more than 100 were wounded in the attack.
A police officer at the festival said hundreds of pilgrims were standing shoulder to shoulder before the blast.One witness, Rohullah, 21, who saw the explosion from a nearby rooftop, said it had sent bodies and limbs flying into the air.
A spokesman for the healthy ministry confirmed at least 14 people, including two women and a child, had been killed and 105 others wounded.
A shopkeeper, who witnessed the blast, said he and his mother were delivering food to the worshippers when the bomb went off. "It was very loud. My ears went deaf and I was blown three metres," said Mustafa, who uses only one name. "There was smoke and blood on the floor of the shrine. There were people lying everywhere."
Stunned and tearful locals milled around the scene of the attack as loudspeakers still played recorded verses of the Qur'an.
The shrine is located in Murad Khane, a mainly Shia neighbourhood along the Kabul river, close to the defence ministry.
There was no immediate claim of responsibility for what is believed to be the worst sectarian attack in Afghanistan's bloody recent history.
Although such attacks have become commonplace in neighbouring Pakistan and parts of the Middle East such as Iraq, they have not occurred in Afghanistan.
Mohammad Bakir Shaikzada, the top Shia cleric in Kabul, said that it was the first time that Shias had been attacked in decades. He said he could not remember a similar attack having taken place.
"This is a crime against Muslims during the holy day of Ashura. We Muslims will never forget these attacks. It is the enemy of the Muslims who are carrying them out," he told the Associated Press. He did not know who could have carried out such an attack.
In a separate attack four people were killed, including one Afghan soldier, when a bomb exploded in the Afghan city of Mazar-i-Sharif, a district police official said.
The bomb, which was carried on a bicycle, exploded near a mosque.
</text>
</article>