<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
  <articleID>25270</articleID>
  <groupName>http://emm.newsbrief.eu/NewsBrief/moreclusteredition/en/jrep-4e2586973c0e76af32b4f04828c417da.html</groupName>
  <groupID>g462</groupID>
  <articleTimestamp>5/21/2012 6:15:00 AM</articleTimestamp>
  <text>Yemeni military police collect evidence at the site of a suicide bomb attack in Sanaa on May 21, 2012. A Yemeni soldier packing powerful explosives under his uniform blew himself up in the middle of an army battalion the Yemeni capital, killing 96 troops and wounding around 300, a military official and medics said.  PHOTO: AFP
SANAA: A suicide bomber with explosives strapped under his uniform killed more than 90 people at a military parade rehearsal in the Yemeni capital Sanaa on Monday, an attack which will alarm Washington as its involvement in the front-line state deepens.
The bombing also wounded about 200 people, officials said, making it the bloodiest single incident in the city in recent years.
The attack, along with an ambush on Sunday on a US military training team, indicated their campaign could be entering a dangerous new stage.
The United States sees Yemen as a vital front in its global war on militants and is increasing its military support for the government of President Abd-Rabbu Mansour Hadi.
The defence ministry said at least 90 soldiers were killed and 222 wounded.
One investigator said preliminary findings suggested the suicide bomber was a rogue soldier rather than a man in a disguise.
The usual security procedure for such an event would involve checks being made on the soldiers at their bases before they are transported to the site of the parade in army vehicles.
The wounded were ferried to hospital in taxis.
In response to two days of violence, Hadi sacked two senior commanders and allies of his predecessor Saleh, whom he replaced in February.
The impoverished state has seen a spate of deadly attacks since Hadi took office saying he would extinguish an insurgency, which until now has been concentrated in the south.
At least seven militants and seven soldiers were killed in clashes when fighters attacked an army position near the southern town of Zinjibar on Monday, residents and a local official said.
Yemeni troops closed in on the southern militant-held town of Jaar on Sunday in heavy fighting, part of a new US-backed offensive launched earlier this month to regain control of territory and towns seized by Ansar al-Sharia.
The parade was scheduled for Tuesday to mark the unification of north and south Yemen, previously separate states, which were merged in 1990.
</text>
</article>